<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Historical description of the glorious conquest of the city of Buda, the capital city of the kingdom of Hungary, by the victorious arms of the thrice illustrious and invincible Emperor Leopold I, under the conduct of His Most Serene Highness, the Duke of Lorraine, and the Elector of Bavaria</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3381</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13191091</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13191091</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 421:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Historical description of the glorious conquest of the city of Buda, the capital city of the kingdom of Hungary, by the victorious arms of the thrice illustrious and invincible Emperor Leopold I, under the conduct of His Most Serene Highness, the Duke of Lorraine, and the Elector of Bavaria</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, October 1st, 1686. R. L'Estrange"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Trinity College Library, Cambridge, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Leopold --  I, --  Holy Roman Emperor, 1640-1705.</term>
               <term>Charles --  V, --  Duke of Lorraine, 1643-1690.</term>
               <term>Maximilian --  II Emanuel, --  Elector of Bavaria, 1662-1726.</term>
               <term>Buda (Hungary) --  History --  Siege, 1686.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98375:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Hiſtorical Deſcription OF THE GLORIOUS CONQUEST Of the CITY of BUDA, THE Capital CITY of the KINGDOM of HUNGARY,</p>
            <p>By the Victorious Arms of the Thrice Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious and Invincible Emperor <hi>LEOPOLD</hi> I.</p>
            <p>Under the Conduct of his Moſt Serene Highneſs, the Duke of <hi>LORRAINE,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>BAVARIA.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>LICENSED,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>October</hi> 1ſt. 1686.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>R. L'Eſtrange.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavell,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church-Yard.</hi> MDCLXXXVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98375:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98375:2"/>
            <head>THE BOOKSELLER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>AFTER ſo many disjointed Relations of Truth, and uncertain Reports hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and confus'd one among another, we do here preſent the Reader with a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Diary of the whole Siege of <hi>Buda</hi> from the very firſt March of the Army that lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, till the end of the Siege, which terminated in the Winning of the Town. The Gentleman that wrote it in <hi>French</hi> was, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, an Eye-witneſs of moſt of thoſe bloody Tranſactions, as being an Imperialiſt, and upon the Theatre himſelf. Nor is it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to miſtruſt the Credit of a Perſon, whoſe Zeal for the Common Cauſe makes him ſo diligent as not to omit the leaſt Particular that may contribute to the Honour of ſo many
<pb facs="tcp:98375:3"/>Renowned Commanders, without detracting in the leaſt from the Gallantry of the Defendants. So that the Paſſages of every Day, thus clos'd and join'd together, yields a full Proſpect of the Induſtry, Vigilancy, Courage, Reſolution, Experience and Conduct of Generals exact in Martial Affairs; and the Indefatigable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and Valour of Laborious and well-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd Soldiers. A Piece, which when the Curious in Hiſtory have read, they will find the Story of the moſt Famous Siege in the World; the Aſſailants equalling, if not ſurpaſſing <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſurrounding <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and <hi>Abdi Baſha</hi> no leſs bravely obſtinate in defending his Truſt, than <hi>Villerius</hi> upon the Walls of <hi>Rhodes.</hi> Of which I ſhall ſay no more in the Epiſtle, ſince the Book is ſo near at hand.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98375:3"/>
            <head>AN Hiſtorical Deſcription OF THE CONQUEST Of the CITY of BUDA.</head>
            <p>THE Diviſions and Miſ-underſtandings that have reign'd among the Chriſtian Princes, gave the Mahometans an opportunity to ſurpriſe ſome by Policy and Stratagem, others by the force of their triumphing Arms, and to conſtrain ſome, that were not in a condition to ſtop the Torrent of their formidable Armies, to put themſelves under their Protection, and acknowledge, by the payment of an Annual Tribute, the power of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire; which in leſs than four Centuries has ſpread it ſelf to ſuch a vaſt Extent, and become ſo terrible to all the Earth, that their Chief Sultans would ſuffer no Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, nor acknowledge any Equals. True it is, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>Tamerlan</hi> King of the <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Parthians,</hi> had the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98375:4"/>good fortune to tame the Pride and haughty Arrogance of <hi>Bajazet:</hi> But his death, which happen'd in the flower of his Age, reviv'd the dejected courage of the <hi>Turks</hi> in ſuch a manner, that they not only regain'd the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Countries which that victorious Prince had wreſted out of their hands, but in proceſs of time forc'd the <hi>Parthians</hi> alſo and the <hi>Tartars</hi> to do them Homage, to pay 'em Tribute, and ſubmit to ſuch Laws as the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperours thought fit to impoſe upon 'em.</p>
            <p>Theſe Barbarians have often attempted to bring <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> under their ſubjection; to which purpoſe they have ſeveral times, like an Inundation, with all the Forces of the Eaſt over-run <hi>Hungary, Auſtria,</hi> and the adjacent Countries; and had accompliſhed their deſigns, had not God in meer pity and compaſſion, heard the Prayers of all Chriſtendom, and twice miraculouſly delivered the City of <hi>Vienna</hi> from the fury of the Infidels: Firſt, in the year 1529. when <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent with an Army of 300000 fighting Men had reduc'd it to the laſt extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, by means of the bloody Aſſaults with which he harraſs'd the Defendants without ceaſing; yet was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to raiſe his Siege upon the approach of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth. The ſecond time, in the year 1683. when a numerous <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, conſiſting of above 200000. Men, under the Command of the Grand Viſier <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> attack'd that important Bulwark of <hi>Germany,</hi> with ſo much fury, during a Siege of three Months, carried on with the greateſt vigor and obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that had been known for many Ages paſt; ſo that the place was driven to its laſt ſhifts, and had certainly been forc'd to undergo the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Yoke, had not the God of Battels rais'd the <hi>Polonians, Bavarians, Saxons,</hi> and other Subjects of the Empire, to follow their ſeveral Princes, to the Succour of the capital City of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria;</hi> where they all equally ſhar'd the honour of fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Infidels, and putting them to a ſhameful flight,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98375:4"/>with the loſs of all their Baggage, Riches, Artillery, and a prodigious quantity of warlike Ammunition and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; and above fifty thouſand of their number ſlain.</p>
            <p>Since which time God approving the juſtice of our thrice Illuſtrious and Invincible Emperour's Cauſe, has in ſuch a manner bleſt his victorious Armies, under the Conduct of the Brave and Generous Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and the moſt Serene Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> through the great Victories they have gain'd, and the glorious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts they have made, during the whole courſe of four <hi>Campagnes</hi> together, that they have ſtruck a Terror over all the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire: So that the people not knowing where the fault lay, have miſerably put to death the principal Miniſters of the Port, and the beſt Officers of their Armies, imputing to them the cauſe of God's wrath, as now intending to deſtroy their Empire, and exterminate the Law of their Prophet, for engaging them in an unjuſt War, contrary to the opinion of their <hi>Mufti,</hi> who is the Oracle of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and to whom thoſe Infidels give as much credit, as the Chriſtians do to the Traditions and Writings of the true Prophets, and Doctors of the Church. This <hi>Mufti,</hi> who is the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, and Diſpenſer, and conſequently the Head of the Mahometan Law, was the only perſon in the <hi>Divan,</hi> who endeavour'd to diſſwade the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> from entring into a War with the Emperor, in favour of <hi>Tecke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> foretelling him the curſes that would fall upon his head, the hazard he would run of loſing his Empire, and ſeeing it ſhar'd among the Chriſtian Princes; ſaying withal, That God would never endure, that the <hi>Muſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who had always been ſo punctual in the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Treaties, ſhould violate a League two years before its expiration, and enter into an unjuſt War, which would infallibly draw upon their heads the anger of the Almighty. And indeed he miſs'd but little of moving the credulous People, and rouſing up in their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98375:5"/>minds an averſion to a War ſo fatal and ruinous to their Repoſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grand Signior</hi> to remedy ſo many diſorders, and prevent the miſchiefs threatned him from his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, uſed all the means imaginable to put an end to this Bloody War; to which end he offer'd to make a Peace with the Emperour upon Articles favourable to Chriſtendom; and the Court of <hi>Vienna</hi> having rejected his Propoſitions, he addreſſed himſelf to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Republic of <hi>Venice,</hi> to bring 'em to a particular accommodation, and to break that Sacred League which our Holy Father <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. ſo politick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contriv'd, and carry'd on at the expence of the Treaſures of the Church, for the good of the Cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Propagation of the True Faith.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the great War-like preparations which the Emperour made in his Hereditary Countries, and other parts of <hi>Germany</hi> were carry'd on ſo vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, that all things were ready by the time appointed, to thunder in upon the Turkiſh Garriſons. The Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, the vaſt number of Bombs, Granado's, Shells, and Fire-works, the inventions of a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Monk, and the Sieur <hi>Gonzales,</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ingineer, were ſo dreadful, that well there could not any doubt be made of the happy iſſue of one of the moſt glorious and daring En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes that had been undertaken in a long time: And though the Siege of <hi>Buda</hi> were in vain attempted in the year 1684. at what time it coſt us the blood of 10000. Chriſtians, the diſappointment of one Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne, and the expence of ſo much Treaſure; yet was not the Imperial Court diſcourag'd from a ſecond at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, well knowing that upon the Conqueſt of that important Capital, depended all the reſt of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the neighbouring Countries.</p>
            <p>True it is, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was not more ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the firſt Siege, than thoſe other Generals which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98375:5"/>had preceded him in that Enterpriſe; however he fail'd not to acquire great honour, and made it apparent, that he might be compar'd with the moſt renowned Captains, which paſt Ages have admir'd, by that noble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat which he made in the face of a numerous Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and an Army of the Enemies, little inferiour to his own; who durſt not make the leaſt attempt upon his Rear, for fear of having no better ſucceſs than at the time of the Siege, during which the Duke had three times beaten the Seraſquier's Army; and had it not been that the Winter was already come, which caus'd a ſcarcity of Forrage, and other neceſſaries for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of the Armies, and ſome little miſ-underſtandings among the Generals, perhaps there might have been no need of a ſecond Siege.</p>
            <p>In the Council of War that was held the laſt year in preſence of the Emperor, to conſult what was to be done the next Summer, there were ſome who preſently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> and to keep the Fortreſs of <hi>Newhauſel</hi> blockt up, that ſo it might be compelled to yield of it ſelf; which was rejected by others, who were of opinion, That Thorn was firſt to be pulled out of the foot, and that the Expedition of <hi>Buda</hi> was to be reſerv'd for the preſent year, as was done. In the mean time there were ſeveral Councils of War, wherein the Sentiments of the Generals were very much divided; the moſt part affirming, That it was firſt requiſite to be Maſters of <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> to prevent the Turks from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of it as a place of Retreat, and ſheltering their Army under the Cannon of that Fortreſs, as the Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier had done at the laſt Siege, to the great vexation of our Forces. Others were for marching directly to the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> taking that City, and then lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a part of the Army for the preſervation of that important Paſſage; to waſt all the Enemies Country, and ſo to ſit down before <hi>Buda.</hi> Others were for the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98375:6"/>Recovery of <hi>Agria,</hi> and the Fortreſs of <hi>Mongats,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to exterminate the Remainder of that Arch-Rebel <hi>Teckely</hi>'s adherents; of which, the Reduction of thoſe two places would clear all the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Hungary.</hi> Some propos'd to act with two Armies apart: That the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Bavaria</hi> ſhould march into the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Hungary,</hi> and draw one part of the Enemies Forces that way, while the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> Beſieg'd <hi>Alba Regalis;</hi> and that the <hi>Croatian</hi> Army under General <hi>Schultz</hi> ſhould march toward the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck.</hi> There were very few that concluded poſitively for the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> which was nevertheleſs the Enterprize that the Emperor and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had reſolv'd to put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whatever it coſt 'em, that they might have the reſt of <hi>Hungary</hi> at a cheaper rate, keep a door open to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade,</hi> and Winter fifty or ſixty thouſand <hi>Germans,</hi> in the Kingdom, where the year before they could not Winter above twenty thouſand.</p>
            <p>This Deſign thus concluded upon, was kept very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, even from the Generals themſelves, to whom the Emperour upon their diſmiſſion declar'd, that he would ſend his Reſolution what he would have done to the general Rendezvous, which was appointed to be in the Plains of <hi>Barkan,</hi> upon the thirtieth of <hi>May.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Auxiliary Forces of <hi>Bavaria, Brandenburgh, Saxony,</hi> and the <hi>Circles,</hi> could not be there ſo ſoon, they were delay'd for ſome days. In the mean time the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces march'd from all parts to the place aſſign'd, as well by Water as Land; ſo that it was a lovely ſight to ſee the <hi>Danube</hi> cover'd with ſuch an infinite number of Barks and Barges laden with Soldiers, great Guns, Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Proviſions, Bullets, Bombs, Granado's, Carcaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Shovels, Pick-Axes, and other Inſtruments fit for the Siege of a Town.</p>
            <p>Upon the 20th. of <hi>May</hi> the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Newſtadt,</hi> to which place the whole Court was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98375:6"/>come from <hi>Vienna</hi> ſome days before. There his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoral Highneſs, together with the Arch-Dutcheſs his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy were received by their Imperial Highneſſes, with all the Marks of a tender Affection, beſeeming the near Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between Perſonages of that illuſtrious Quality, the Cannon of the Garriſon being three times diſcharged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Entrance.</p>
            <p>Upon the 23d. being Aſcenſion-Day, the Elector went to viſit the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who was come to <hi>Oldenburgh,</hi> though ſomewhat indiſpoſed, and returned the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening to <hi>Newſtadt:</hi> Where his Electoral Highneſs ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had ſeveral Conferences about the opening of the <hi>Campaign,</hi> and taken leave of their Imperial Majeſties, and the Electreſs his Wife, he departed the ſecond of <hi>June,</hi> with the Acclamations of the whole Court, and People, and the Prayers and good Wiſhes of all, That God would be pleaſed to preſerve the Life of that young Prince, who was going ſo generouſly to expoſe his own, and the Lives of his Subjects in ſuch a Holy War, againſt the ſworn Enemy of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>After that his ſaid Electoral Highneſs arriving at <hi>Comor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rha,</hi> was there received by the Commanders, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of the City, with Peals of Cannon, and three Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys of ſmall Shot, ranged in double Files, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted to the Lodging prepared for him. The next day the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who had put himſelf at the Head of the Imperial Army, near <hi>Barkan,</hi> came to give a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit to his Electoral Highneſs, and view the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which was to that purpoſe drawn up in Battle-Array in the Fields, near <hi>Comorrha,</hi> where Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> commanded next under his Electoral Highneſs, in the quality of General of the Cavalry, Count <hi>Serini</hi> in quality of General of Artillery. The Marqueſs <hi>de la Vergne,</hi> and the Count <hi>de Fontaign,</hi> acted there as Lieutenant-General Marſhals of the Camp; the Count <hi>d'Aſpremont,</hi> and Prince <hi>Eugenius</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> ſerved as Generals of <hi>Battalia's.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98375:7"/>The Baron of <hi>Beck,</hi> who was alſo nominated to ſerve under his Electoral Highneſs, lying ſick at <hi>Newhauſel</hi> of a dangerous Feaver, was diſpenc'd with; but his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Infantry, which was in the number of thoſe which the Emperour had made choice of to re-inforce the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> fail'd not to be there under the Command of the Lieutenant Colonel.</p>
            <p>The 10th of <hi>June</hi> Count <hi>Straatman,</hi> great Chancellour to the Emperour, arriv'd at the general Rendezvous near <hi>Barkan,</hi> to compoſe certain differences that were riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Generals upon certain Punctilio's of Command, and allotment ordain'd of who and who to ſerve in the ſeparate Armies of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> This Miniſter of State, who is one of the moſt dextrous Perſons, and profoundeſt Politicians of his Age, caus'd a Council of War to be call'd, where he ſo well manag'd the diſpoſitions of the Generals, that he gave them all the ſatisfaction imaginable: Which done, he ſhew'd them the Imperial Commiſſion, containing the Emperour's orders to begin the Campagne with the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> exhorting them withal to behave themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Qualities in an Enterprize of ſuch great importance, upon which depended not only the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Conqueſts, the eſtabliſhment of his Crown Imperial, and the welfare of Chriſtendom, but alſo the Ruin of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, which after the loſs of ſo conſiderable a place could not prevent the other Cities of <hi>Hungary</hi> from returning under the Obedience of their Lawful Sovereign, nor ſtop the progreſs of the Chriſtian Arms. So that though the Generals expected poſitive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to beſiege <hi>Agria,</hi> or <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> it is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd how much overjoy'd they were when they heard that the Emperour was reſolv'd they ſhould ſit down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Buda.</hi> And this News being ſpread among the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Soldiers of both Armies, they teſtify'd their particular ſatisfaction, and the eager deſire which they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98375:7"/>had to haſten to the place where they ſhould have ſuch noble opportunities to give ſignal proofs of their Valour, and revenge the death of their Comrades, which had laid their bones in the Trenches of the former Siege. The Volunteers, which were already numbred to be above ſix thouſand that reſorted to this Stage of War, from <hi>Germany, Spain, Italy, France, England,</hi> the Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and all part of <hi>Europe,</hi> of all Qualities and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, to win honour under the Imperial Enſigns, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted the greateſt heat and zeal imaginable to ſignalize their Courage in ſo glorious an Enterprize.</p>
            <p>The Auxiliaries of <hi>Saxony</hi> commanded by the Prince of <hi>Saxen-Hall,</hi> and Major-General, the Count <hi>de Trautmanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorf,</hi> who had taken their march through <hi>Moravia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by this time alſo arriv'd at the Rendezvous, the Generals reſolv'd to decamp, without ſtaying any longer for the Forces of the Circles, or thoſe of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> who having choſen the way of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and the narrow ſtreights of <hi>Jabluncka,</hi> march'd but ſlowly, and could not arrive ſo ſoon.</p>
            <p>Thereupon the Armies diſlodg'd the 12th of <hi>June,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> Eve, by break of day: The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> taking the Road that led to the Bridge of <hi>Gran,</hi> which his Army paſs'd the 13th. The Troops of <hi>Saxony</hi> keeping the Van. The Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> held his march on this ſide the <hi>Danaw,</hi> that he might make himſelf Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the City of <hi>Peſt,</hi> before he ſate down before <hi>Buda.</hi> While the two Armies march'd thus on both ſides the <hi>Danaw,</hi> the Count of <hi>Rabata,</hi> Commiſſary-General, caus'd a prodigious number of Gabions and Bavins to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd, for making of which the Soldiers were ſtill em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, as they came to their Rendezvous, to keep 'em from idleneſs, which were all ſent with the great Guns, Ammunition, Proviſion, Hay, and other neceſſary Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for the ſubſiſtence of the Armies.</p>
            <p>The 14th. The Body of the main Army advanc'd ſo far as till they came under <hi>Vicegrad,</hi> but the ſmaller Artillery,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98375:8"/>and the Reer-guard were conſtrain'd to ſtay behind by reaſon of the narrow ways through which they were to paſs. The <hi>Bavarian</hi> Army quarter'd that night near <hi>Vaccia,</hi> on the other ſide of the <hi>Danaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 15th. The Imperial Cavalry continu'd their march for an hour beyond <hi>Vicegrad,</hi> followed by the Infantry, and Artillery. And then it was that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent out a commanded Party to diſcover the Enemy, who met with a ſmall Party of the <hi>Turks,</hi> that preſently betook themſelves to flight; but ours had the good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to overtake 'em, and after they had kill'd ſome, to make five Priſoners, whom they brought to our Camp. Where being examin'd, they unanimouſly declar'd, that the Inhabitants of <hi>Agria</hi> and <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> fearing a Siege, had ſecur'd the beſt of their Goods in the City of <hi>Buda,</hi> which together with both the other places were provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded both with Men, and all things neceſſary to ſuſtain a long Siege, till Relief came.</p>
            <p>The 16th. They came within an hours march of <hi>Buda,</hi> none of the Troops of the Garriſon appearing all this while to obſerve our countenances.</p>
            <p>The 17th. The Cavalry made a halt to reſt themſelves, and to give the Infantry and the Artillery time to come up. At what time the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> commanded three thouſand Men to make ſome thouſands of Gabions and Bavins, and began to lay a Bridge of Boats over the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to the Iſland of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> thereby to joyn together both ſides of the <hi>Danaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 18th. The Baron of <hi>Diependael,</hi> General of Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, inveſted the City of <hi>Buda</hi> with one part of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry, while the Infantry came up and took their Poſts about half a League from the place; and then they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the Lines of Circumvallation. At what time a great Party of the Garriſon, both Horſe and Foot, ſhew'd themſelves without <hi>Vienna</hi> Gate. But they retreated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the City, upon the approach of a detachment of the Imperial Cavalry, which was commanded to charge 'em.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98375:8"/>But then the beſieged beſtowed upon us eight Peals of their Cannon, though without doing any more hurt than only killing one ſingle Pioneer, by reaſon they ſhot at too great a diſtance.</p>
            <p>The 19th. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> caus'd the Army to advance as far as the hot Baths, of which he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter, without any oppoſition, (the <hi>Turks</hi> having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon'd that Poſt the day before) and took up his Head Quarters about a quarter of a League from the place. The ſame day the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter of the City of <hi>Peſt,</hi> which the <hi>Turks</hi> had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, after they had carry'd off their Cannon, Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Proviſions into <hi>Buda,</hi> and broken down part of the Bridge of Communication between the one place and the other. About the ſame time our <hi>Croats</hi> ſcouting up and down met a Turkiſh <hi>Chaous</hi> with a Convoy of forty Spahi's, who carry'd Letters from the Port to the Grand Viſier of <hi>Buda:</hi> Him they brought Priſoner to the Camp, where his Letters were read, containing only ſtrict Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the Viſier, to be watchful over the Security of the Places that depended upon his Government, and to aſſure him of ſpeedy and powerful ſuccour, in caſe of an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack.</p>
            <p>The 20th. The Bridg over the <hi>Danaw</hi> was finiſhed. Some of the Enemies Cavalry alſo the ſame Day ſallied out of the Town, with a deſign to cut off our <hi>Advancd Guards;</hi> but his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having timely notice thereof, ſent 4 Squadrons of Horſe to repel 'em; with whom joined alſo ſeveral Volunteers; upon whoſe approach the Enemy retreated, not daring to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage. The ſame Day the Artillery arrived in the Camp, and two Batteries were begun to be raiſed againſt the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Town, which was the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s Attack, the Count of <hi>Starenbergh</hi> doing the duty of the Day, as Camp-Marſhal-General. That Evening the Trenches were open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and a <hi>Janiſary</hi> ſurren dring himſelf to our Camp, report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the other Priſoners had done before, that there
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98375:9"/>were not above eight Thouſand Souldiers in the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for that the Vizier had ſent ſome few days before a Reinforcement of two Thouſand Men to <hi>Agria,</hi> and an equal number to <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> in regard the <hi>Turks</hi> never dreamt that the Imperialiſts had determined a ſecond Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> which had proved ſo fatal to 'em but two Years ago. This Deſerter likewiſe ſaid, that the Place was abundantly provided with Victuals, and Warlike Ammunition, to maintain a long Siege. Moreover, that the Vizier <hi>Abdi Baſſa</hi> was no great Soldier, fitter to make a Merchant of, than a Governour, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently deſpiſed by the Soldiers. That he had aſſembled in the public Piazza of the City, all the Captains and Soldiers, and had there with a ſtudied Harangue, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted 'em to behave themſelves according to their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and gloriouſly to maintain the honour of the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant;</hi> adding withal, that he had Orders from the Grand Signior, to defend the Place to the laſt dorp of his Blood; which he was reſolved to do, hoping that they would do the like in Expectation of that Relief, which the Grand Signior would infallibly ſend them. To whom the Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and Spahi's replied, that they were ready to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice their Lives in the Service of his Highneſs and defence of their Law, upon Condition nevertheleſs, that the Grand <hi>Vizier</hi> would pay them down upon the Nail, ten Crowns a Head; that he would ſet at Liberty the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Souldiers detained in the Priſons, whatever their Crimes might be; and that the Vizier would not hold out to the laſt Extremity, leſt the ſame Misfortune ſhould befal them, as befel the Garriſon of <hi>New-hauſel:</hi> all which Conditions the Vizier promiſed exactly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</p>
            <p>The 21ſt. The Trenches were relieved, upon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s Attack, by Monſieur <hi>Fonck,</hi> Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel of the Regiment of <hi>Souches.</hi> And the ſame day, the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> having left a ſufficient ſtrength in <hi>Peſt,</hi> and paſſed the Bridge of Boats, to St. <hi>Andrew's</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98375:9"/>arrived with his Army, before the Place, and took his Poſt on the ſame part of the Town, where he had commanded in the former Siege, that is to ſay, next to the Caſtle and the High Town, to form a ſecond Attack; the third being reſerved for the <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> which were expected in a few Days, and were to be re-inforced with the Troops of <hi>Suabia</hi> and <hi>Franconia.</hi> That Night the Enemy fired furiouſly upon our Men, that wrought hard in making their Approaches, and raiſing their Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, of whom there were about ſeven or eight Killed, and as many Wounded.</p>
            <p>The 22d. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent all the Imperial and <hi>Bavarian</hi> Cavalry, under the Command of General <hi>Palſi, Gondola,</hi> and others, to Quarter about <hi>Alba Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> to conſume the Forrage in thoſe Places, and keep that Garriſon in continual Alarm, reſerving in his Camp no more than a Thouſand <hi>Bavarian,</hi> and three Thouſand Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Horſe, to ſecure the Pioneers. That Night we brought to Perfection a Battery againſt the low Town, upon which were planted twelve Pieces of Cannon, which played all that Day, without ceaſing: We had five Men Killed, and ſome Wounded.</p>
            <p>The 23d. By Break of day, we continued Firing with ſuch good Succeſs, that there was a Breach made in the Wall of the Low Town, about twenty Paces broad. All this while the <hi>Bavarians</hi> wrought hard in making their Approaches, of whom there were ſome alſo Killed and Wounded.</p>
            <p>The 24th. The Breach being enlarged, they gave an Aſſault toward Evening, and made themſelves Maſters of the Wall, without much reſiſtance, for that they who were to have defended it, were retired into the High Town, after they had fired only once. In this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet we had a Captain of Foot, a Lieutenant of Granadeers, four Soldiers, and ſix Volunteers Killed, and ſeven or eight Wounded. And from this time forward, they began to attack the City, according to the due forms of Art;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98375:10"/>and a reſolution was taken, that the Trenches ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day be relieved by a Serjeant General of Battalia, as well upon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s Side, as that of the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi>'s: and ſo upon the 25th. The Count of <hi>Souches,</hi> Lieutenant Camp-Marſhal General, and <hi>Diepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dael,</hi> General of Battalia, relieved the Trenches: at what time, little elſe was done, but only they ſecured their Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Wall of the Low Town, and re-open'd a Gate, which the <hi>Turks</hi> had cloſed up to the Right hand, at a good diſtance from the Breach, where they had taken their Poſt; and to the end the Pioneers might work more ſafely, the Count <hi>de Souches</hi> cauſed ſome adjoining Houſes to be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red where ſome <hi>Fuſeleer Turks</hi> were burnt. The ſame day the <hi>Bavarians</hi> finiſhed a ſmall Battery upon St. <hi>Gerards Mount,</hi> which the Enemy had abandoned, from whence they ſhot ſome ſmall Bombs into the High Town, to try the Effect. They alſo finiſhed another great Battery to beat down the great Roundel that joins the Caſtle to the High Town. The ſame day Count <hi>Budiani</hi> preſented to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſome Colours, which he had won from a Party of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Cavalry, which convoyed about fourteen or fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Barks, laden with Women and Children, belonging to the Officers of <hi>Buda,</hi> who were endeavouring to make their Eſcape, with all the wealth of the City, to <hi>Belgrade;</hi> and whom his <hi>Huſſars,</hi> and <hi>Heydukes,</hi> reinforced with a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Imperial Dragoons, had ſurprized and routed near St. <hi>Margarets</hi> Iſland, got a rich Booty, and taken Ninety two Women and Children, and among the reſt, the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier of <hi>Buda</hi>'s Wife.</p>
            <p>The 26th. They wrought upon ſeveral traverſe Lines, and to finiſh the Approaches, to ſecure our Lodgments in the Low Town, which were furniſhed with two Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Soldiers, and a good number of Pioneers, who met with great difficulty to advance their Works, the Ground being very rugged, and Stony. The ſame day the Grand Maſter of the <hi>Teutonic</hi> Order, perceiving that our Workmen in the Low Town might be eaſily aſſailed and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98375:10"/>beaten by the <hi>Turks,</hi> ſent to Count <hi>Starenbergh</hi> Camp-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal General for ſome Infantry, who thereupon ſent him ſix Battalions, <hi>viz.</hi> That of <hi>Starenbergh, Newbourg, Mansfield, Souches, Diependael,</hi> and <hi>Tungen,</hi> who were poſted along the Wall, to ſecure the Workmen. The ſame day alſo two Deſerters, who pretended themſelves to be <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> ſurrendred themſelves, and confirmed what had been ſaid before, that the Garriſon conſiſted of no more than eight Thouſand fighting Men, and that by the order of the <hi>Viſier Baſſa,</hi> they had begun to take away the Roofs of the Houſes, and to unpave the Streets, on purpoſe to prevent the Effects of the Bombs. Toward Evening, between ſix and ſeven a Clock, the <hi>Turks</hi> ſallied forth, making hideous outcries, on purpoſe to ſcare thoſe that were poſted near the Roundel, toward the Water-ſide; but they were ſo well received, that they retired in great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. For Camp-Marſhal General <hi>Starenbergh</hi> came timely in with two Battalions of thoſe Men that had been poſted the day before, behind the Wall; which had he not done, the Enemy without doubt had made a great Slaughter of our Pioneers. The Enemy was purſued about two Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Paces from the Trenches, and our Soldiers brought off ſeveral of the Heads of the <hi>Turks,</hi> which they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Highenſs the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who cauſed a Ducket in Gold to be given to each Soldier, for every Head. Captain <hi>Burger</hi> of <hi>Starenbergh's</hi> Regiment was there wounded, with ten or twelve Soldiers, and as many ſlain outright.</p>
            <p>The ſame day the <hi>Bavarians</hi> finiſhed two Batteries for Bombs, on each ſide their Grand Battery. They alſo carryed on their Trenches above a Hundred Paces, they alſo made three croſs Lines, and a Place for drawing up the Soldiers for the Guard of their Battery. The <hi>Turks</hi> alſo fired very furiouſly upon us with their great Guns, but did us no more Miſchief, than only to kill us two Men.</p>
            <p>The 27th. Finiſhed the Works which they had begun
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98375:11"/>in the Night; they made new Traverſes; ſome Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers were put into the Moſque of the Low Town; a Poſt was taken upon the Right hand, near the Gate which makes the Angle of the High Town; they enlarged and deepened their Lines, to render 'em capable of holding more Men; and almoſt finiſhed the Grand Battery, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Loſs, ſaving one Man Killed, and ſome Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. That Morning the Enemy ſhewed themſelves in the ſame Part as the day before, ranged as if they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned ſome Encounter, but perceiving we were ready to receive them, they retired within the Circuit of their Walls, without enterprizing any thing. About eleven a Clock at Noon, they ſallied out Horſe and Foot to diſlodge our Men that were poſted on the Right hand; but having diſcharged one ſingle Volley, and perceiving the Count of <hi>Hoffkirken, Dunewald</hi>'s Lieutenant Collonel, haſtning to the relief of ours, with the Horſe-guard, they regain'd the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, leaving twenty of their Men dead upon the Spot, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Wounded, which they carried along with them. Of ours, there were but two killed, and five or fix wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The ſame day came another Deſerter, who reported that the Governour was very much perplexed, foreſeeing the inevitable loſs of the City, which the Grand Signior had committed to his Charge; as alſo for that in his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, he loſt the beſt and choiceſt of his Men, without any hopes of ruining our Works; but that nothing griev'd him ſo much to the Heart, as the taking of his own, and the Wives of the principal Officers of the Garriſon, by the <hi>Heydukes, Huſſars,</hi> and Dragoons, when they thought they had been in a place of ſafety. The ſame day alſo finiſhed a Battery on the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack, levelled againſt the Caſtle and the Rondel next the City.</p>
            <p>They 29th. They drew a Line of Communication four Hundred Paces in length from the Poſt of the Right hand Angle, to the middle Gate, and another Line were made to go to the middle Battery, upon which was Planted twelve Pieces of Cannon. They alſo wrought to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98375:11"/>raiſe a ſmall Battery near the great one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, whereon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> four Mortar pieces, which were brought thither in the Evening with ſome Waggons full of Bombs. The ſame time the Beſieged began to caſt Bombs and Stones upon ours; ſo that a Captain and 16 Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were wounded that night, and ſome ſlain. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> then foreſeeing that there might be a ſcarcity of Horſe-meat in the Camp, ſent the greateſt part of the Baggage Horſes into the Meadows that were aſſign'd them between <hi>Newhauſel</hi> and <hi>Gran.</hi> And then it was that General <hi>Dunewald,</hi> who commanded the Cavalrie, encamped near <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> gave Advice to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, That the Turks having quitted the Caſtle of <hi>Bathyan</hi> upon the River <hi>Zarwis,</hi> he had placed a Garriſon therein, and that he had made an Attempt upon <hi>Palotta,</hi> a very ſtrong Fort, near <hi>Alba Regalis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 29. we continued to finiſh our Works, and his ſerene Highneſs increaſed the number of Pioneers to ſix hundred. The Enemy made no Sallies during theſe two Days, but fir'd more ſuriouſly than uſually to ruine our great Battery. About five <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Clock in the Evening they made a moſt furious Attack upon the Bavarian Attack with 2000 Horſe and Foot, with ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ucceſs, that they put ours into a Confuſion; and the Janiſaries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rowing themſelves into the Approaches, were very buſie in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ining all before 'em; when the Count of <hi>Hoffkirken,</hi> who there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Wonders, flew to the Relief of the Engaged with the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uard of the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi>'s Quarter, and the <hi>Bavarian</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enerals with the Reſerve, ſo that the Combat was very cruel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d bloody on both Sides; but the Enemy was forced to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ound, and was purſued to the very Gates of the City, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>thſtanding the Beſieged continually play'd upon our Men with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir great Guns and ſmall Shot. Prince <hi>Eugenius</hi> of <hi>Savoy</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s in great Danger, having his Horſe killed under him. Prince <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>is</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> and the Generals, <hi>Fontain</hi> and <hi>La Vargne,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lized themſelves in this Action, as did alſo the Volunteers; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t above all the Prince of <hi>Commercy,</hi> who was in the hotteſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Engagement. The <hi>Sieur de Switterdael,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Regiment of <hi>Staina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> was there kill'd, with ſeven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thirty Soldiers, and ſix Volunteers, beſides ſixty two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unded, among which was a Captain, two Lieutenants, and an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſign; but the Loſs of the Turks was much more conſiderable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that our Souldiers brought away ſixty Heads, and by a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſcian</hi> Deſerter we underſtood afterwards that the Turks had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98375:12"/>above two hundred of their Men killed and wounded in that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter. That Evening, upon the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, they began to play the four Mortar Piecey planted near the great Battery, and to ſhoot Bombs upon the Enemies Batteries. Six Culverins alſo were planted upon the old Battery, formerly raiſed to make a Breach in the low Town, deſign'd to play directly upon the Gate of the City, and diſturb the Sallys of the Beſieged.</p>
            <p>The 30. The Forces of <hi>Suabia</hi> and <hi>Franconia</hi> arrived in the Camp, and took the Poſts which had been aſſigned them. All the Night and all the Day were ſpent in advancing our Works, which were ſo numerous, that they could hardly be diſtinguiſhed one from another. This Night there were but two Souldiers killed, and ſome few wounded. The Count of <hi>Souches,</hi> who commanded this day in the Trenches, having ſent three Granadeers to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Diſtance between our Approaches and the Roundel, brought word that it was not above three hundred Paces, and that the Enemy was hard at work in making a deep Trench at the Foot of the Roundel, and that having gone a great way forwarder on the left ſide, than on the right, they had encreaſed their number of Workemen on the right ſide. All night long, Bavins, Gabions, Munition, and Proviſion, were ſent to the Camp in great abundance, through the Care of the Count <hi>de Rabata</hi> Commiſſary General. The ſame day General <hi>Caprara</hi> left the Camp with the Cavalry of <hi>Suabia,</hi> to head the Cavalry encamped near <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> which he was to command in chief. Five Raſcian Shepherds alſo coming out of the City to feed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the Walls, ſurrendred themſelves with above four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sheep to the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi>'s Quarter, who cauſed 'em to be well rewarded. They could give nothing of Information, only that there was a great Conſternation among the Beſieged; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs that they were reſolved to defend themſelves in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Succour which they were promiſed; moreover that our Bombs and Carcaſſes had ſet fire to ſeveral parts of the City, which had been fortunately quenched.</p>
            <p>The firſt of <hi>July.</hi> Yeſterday in the Evening General <hi>Schoning,</hi> who commands the Auxiliary Forces of <hi>Bradenb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgh,</hi> arrived in the Camp: And this Morning Camp-Marſhal-General <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renburgh</hi> ſhewed him the Approaches, and the Attack which was reſerved for his Men; which was toward the water ſide, to the left of the Imperialiſts; after which he was magnificently treated by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and having had a Conference with his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98375:12"/>Highneſs, where was alſo preſent General <hi>Starenburgh,</hi> he returned to meet his Forces that were expected the next day, or the next day after at fartheſt. This morning the Imperaſiſts began to ſhoot from their new Battery of four Pieces carrying twenty four pound Ball. The five Mortar Pieces alſo near the great Battery, continued playing upon the round Tower upon the right Hand, with ſuch Succeſs, that the Beſieged durſt not appear there any more. The ſame day they finiſhed their Works, and made two Redoubts to ſecure a Communication with the great Battery. This Night we had but five wounded and one ſlain; but in the morning Adjutant General <hi>Mercy</hi> was wounded in the Head with a Musket as he was carrying Orders to the Approaches. There was nothing done in the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Quarter this day, only they advanced their Works, and their Batteries had made a Breach in the Rampart without: And the ſame day the remainder of the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Forces arrived, conſiſting of 1400 Foot, which were added to the reſt of the ſame Circle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 2. Our Approaches on the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack ſide were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced within two hundred Paces of the Wall of the City. The night before was finiſhed a Battery of twelve pieces of Cannon, carrying twenty four pound ball; and four Mortar Pieces more were planted near the firſt, that play'd without ceaſing, and fir'd the laſt night a part of the City next the great Church, which burnt till morning. Nevertheleſs we continued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ooting with our great Guns againſt the two firſt round Towers, which were left almoſt defenceleſs. The two Battalians alſo of <hi>Keyſerſtein</hi> and <hi>Croy,</hi> were commanded to reinforce thoſe that lay encamped un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Wall of the low Town. The Enemy likewiſe ſhot down ſeveral Bombs and Stones, without doing us any great Miſchief, only that they kill'd us two or three Soldiers. The ſame day the Troops of <hi>Suabia</hi> began their Line of Circumval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and the next night raiſed a Battery upon the Hill which they poſſeſs. In the mean time the <hi>Bavarians</hi> play'd very furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly againſt the Caſtle and the high Town, and ſhot in ſeveral Bombs, which occaſioned a new Conflagration, which was not quenched in a good while. And now the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive leſt the Turks might in the night time, by the help of ſmall Barks, get in Men and Proviſions into <hi>Buda,</hi> went perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to view the Places adjoyning to <hi>Peſt,</hi> and commanded the Prince of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Regiment of Dragoons to poſt themſelves in the Town<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that they might be ready to aſſiſt the <hi>Hungarians</hi> who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98375:13"/>lay there, and had orders to raiſe certain little Forts upon the Banks of the <hi>Danaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 3. This morning arriv'd the Troops of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> from the other ſide of the <hi>Danaw,</hi> that lay encamped near our Bridge. Soon after came the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to take a view of 'em, and was received by General <hi>Schoning</hi> with three Volleys of Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers rang'd in Battalia, and three Peals of Artillery planted at the head of the Infantry. His Highneſs alſo was entertain'd with much ſplendor at Dinner, and then return'd to his Quarters extreamly ſatisfied to have ſeen ſuch a conſiderable Body of Men, ſtout and active, and ſo well provided with a noble Train of Artillery. The ſame day the Imperialiſts finiſh'd another Line for the defence of their Trenches. They alſo fired very furiouſly with their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non and Mortar Pieces; ſo that they not only made a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Breach in the Wall, but alſo ruin'd the Batteries upon the two firſt Roundels, from whence the Enemy fired without Intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. On the other ſide, the <hi>Bavarians</hi> advanced their Lines to the Caſtle, and raiſed a new Battery on the right hand toward the <hi>Danaw,</hi> upon which they planted nine Mortar Pieces, which did wonderful Execution. Three days before this, they play'd from a Battery of ſeven Demi-Cannons againſt the round Tower, while from another of four Pieces they belabour'd the Flanks: they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe raiſed a new Battery of eight Pieces to beat down the left ſide of the Roundel. Seven men were kill'd in the Lorrain Attack, and ſome wounded. This day in the Afternoon, an Enſign of the Janiſaries rendred himſelf to the Camp, having deſerted his own Party for having kill'd a Turkiſh Officer in a Duel. He aſſured us that of true Janiſaries, there were not above fifteen hundred in the Garriſon; but that what with the <hi>Saphi</hi>'s, <hi>Albanians,</hi> and others, they made up the number of ſeven thouſand fighting Men. He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the Bombs and Carcaſſes had already ruined ſeveral Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and occaſioned great deſtruction both of Men and Cattel. That the Beſieged were very buſie in making a Mine behind the Breach of the Lorrain Attack; and that till that very hour, there had not any perſon entred the place. As for General <hi>Dunewald,</hi> he forbore to proſecute his Deſign upon <hi>Palotta,</hi> finding it was provided with a good Garriſon; a Party of which had kill'd ſome of his Men that went to take a view of the place. Another Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry alſo of the Garriſon of <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> had met withal, and routed ſome Forragers of the Horſe that were quartered in the Neighbourhood, and kill'd among others Count <hi>Papenheim,</hi> Captain of Horſe in the Bavarian Troops.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98375:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 4. They advanced ſo far with their Approaches in the Lorrain Attack, that they were got within a hundred Paces of the Breach of the Roundel on the right hand. The Enemy alſo began to make a Line without the Breach about fifty Paces from our Works, to render the Breach more inacceſſible; and though they fired continually all night long with their Muſquets, and ſlung an infinite number of Stones, we had but thirteen men kill'd and wounded. And now had we fourteen Mortar Pieces planted that ſhot Bombs and Carcaſſes continually without ceaſing. In the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varian Attack, but only what concern'd the ſecuring our Works, and advancing the Batteries. This morning a Polonian that ſerv'd the Turks, render'd himſelf to the Camp, and reported that the beſieged were reſolv'd to Surrender, if they were not reliev'd within a Month: and another Deſerter in the afternoon came and declared that the beſieged had the night before landed five Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men aſhore on <hi>Peſt</hi> ſide, who were to take ſeveral Roads, that one at leaſt might get ſafe to the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> and preſs him to haſten the Relief that he had promis'd. On the other ſide the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent a Detachment of Horſe toward <hi>Voitfar,</hi> to deſtroy the Graſs and Corn, and watch the Motion of the Enemy. Of this ſome Tartars had Intelligence, and ſnapt ſome of our Forragers on the other ſide of the <hi>Danaw;</hi> they alſo took ſome Horſes, and two Grooms belonging to Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> who were in St. <hi>Marget</hi>'s Iſland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 5. Laſt night ſixty Granadeers, with ſome Pioneers, were commanded to go and ruin the Line which the Enemy had the day before begun before the breach of the Roundel, which ſucceeded ſo well, that they filled up the breach without the loſs of more than two Soldiers. By this time alſo the breaches were made wider and wider, as well where the Lorrainers, as where the Bavarians attacked, and what the Turks repaired in the night, was by us overthrown in the day time. And now all the Bavarians were come up and joyned together in their Quarters; upon whom the Enemy made a Sally in the night time; and though they were bravely received, and purfued to the very Gates of the City, yet they loſt many gallant and ſtout Men, and among the reſt the Son of Camp-Marſhal-General <hi>Dorfeling,</hi> an Ingineer, two Lieutenants, and ſeven and twenty Soldiers, beſides the ſame num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber wounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 6. There was a Line of Communication made from the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s Attack to that of the <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> not above
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98375:14"/>fifty Paces from the Gate in the middle and about ſixty Paces from the breach on the right hand. This morning the Cannon played ſo furiouſly, that they utterly beat down the two Roundels with the Curtain; and when night came they ſhot without ceaſing Bombs and Granadoes, that kindled a fire near the Roundel, on the right hand, that laſted three hours. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and General <hi>Starenbergh</hi> ſtay'd till eleven of Clock at night in the Approaches, to encourage the Workmen with their preſence. The <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> alſo had by this time vigorouſly advanced their Works, their Generals of Battalia alternatively relieving one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their Trenches. The Sieur <hi>Fonk,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel to <hi>Souches,</hi> was wounded in the Leg, with ſix Soldiers, and two killed. The <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> had a Captain of Granadeers wounded, with ſix Soldiers, and eight ſlain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 7. Laſt night a great number of Bombs were ſhot into the Town, which did great Execution, in regard the fire was ſeen to blaze out in ſeveral parts of the City; though greater Execution was expected to be done upon the Arrival of <hi>Gonzales</hi> our Ingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer, who was lookt for in the Camp within two or three days, whither the great Guns, Mortar Pieces, Bombs, Carcaſſes, and other Artificial Fire-works were already arrived. This morning the Enemy ſallied out upon the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> Attack with Horſe and Foot, but greatly to their diſadvantage; being ſo vigorouſly receiv'd, that they were forced to retire in great diſorder, being purſued under the very Walls of the City: there were alſo prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Batteries to be ready in two days, when they reſolved to be heard as loud as the reſt of their Friends. Yeſterday the Miners began to work upon the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack to widen the breaches, and this night the ſame was done upon the <hi>Bavarian</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack, where they had by this finiſh'd two new Batteries, the one of ten, the other of ſeven Pieces of Cannon; and a third was raiſing toward the water ſide, to level the attacked Roundel, and a gate through which the beſieged ſallied out very frequently to get into a cloſe way which they had made before the ſaid Roun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del. Yeſterday the <hi>Bavarians</hi> advanc'd their Approaches to the foot of the Caſtle, ſo that they could approach no nearer till the breach were enlarged. And indeed the Works in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack were ſo near the Wall, that they could not advance any nearer without lodging upon the breach. So that there were above fifty men killed and wounded in the three Attacks. Yeſter night the Enemy ſhot a Bomb, which lighting into a barrel of Powder, kill'd nine of our Cannoneers.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98375:14"/>
            <p>The 8th was buſily employ'd upon the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, in raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nearer the Walls two new Batteries of three Demi-Cannons each; and upon the left hand, where we had not carried on our Approaches as upon the left, they advanced their Approaches to the very Wall of the Roundel; which being a work to be done ſo near the Enemy, coſt us five and twenty Soldiers, kill'd and wounded, the moſt part with Stones and Granadoes, among whom was Major General <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngen,</hi> who was upon the Guard of the Trenches with the Count <hi>de Souches.</hi> The Sieur <hi>Biſchoffhanſen</hi> Serjcant Major of one of the <hi>Suabian</hi> Regiments, had his Arm broken with a Musket ſhot; one of <hi>Starenbergh</hi>'s Captains was wounded in the ſhoulder, and <hi>Souches</hi>'s Captain Lieutenant in the Foot. As for the Miners that were ordered to ſapp under the right ſide of the <hi>Roundel,</hi> had not as yet met with any Mines of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. This evening others were ſet to work upon the left ſide of the middle Roundel: and this night Captain <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rger</hi> of <hi>Staren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi>'s Regiment, who had been wounded in the Mouth in the Salley upon the 26th of <hi>June,</hi> died of his wound. Some Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men having found a means to make their Eſcapes out of the City, came the ſame night to our Camp, and aſſured us that there were not above three hundred men that laboured conſtantly in the Mines and the Retrenchment which the Enemies were making behind the Wall, whither to retire in caſe of neceſſity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 9. All night long there was nothing done but ſhooting of Bombs and Carcaſſes into the City, to keep the beſieged in Action, and to deprive them of their Repoſe. But by break of day the Enemy perceiving that we had made a Gallery of Planks to paſs the Miners over to the middle Roundel, rowl'd down ſeveral Bombs, threw Granadoes, and other Fire-works, with all ſorts of combuſtible Materials in ſuch abundance, that the fire caught hold of the Planks, and reduced the Gallery to Aſhes, which obliged our Miners to come away, and deſiſt from their work till the next night. This morning about five a clock the Enemy ſprung a Mine ſome Paces without the Wall, between the middle Roundel and that of the Gate, which ſucceeded ſo well, that it overthrew one of our Mines, where we had ſeven or eight of our Miners, ſome kill'd and ſome wounded. After that they made a Salley, put our Pioneers into diſorder, deſtroy'd ſome of our Works, and poſted themſelves between the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> and <hi>Brandenburghers.</hi> But the Reſerve flying thither from the Main-guard, conſtrained the Enemy, after a ſharp Encounter of half an hour, to regain
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98375:15"/>the City. We had forty of ours kill'd and wounded, and the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> had few leſs, among whom was one of their beſt Cannoneers, and ſome Inferiour Officers. The Enemy left behind them above fourſcore ſlain, beſides what were wounded. But notwithſtanding this rude check to their Succeſs, the beſiegers went on with the ſame vigour as before with their Approaches, their Lines and their Galleries. And the <hi>Bavarians</hi> yeſterday ruin'd the little Gate near the Roundel, with a Battery of ten Pieces of Demy-Cannon, ſo that the breach was already become very broad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> the 10th, In the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack the men labour'd all night to repair the Batteries and Approaches ruin'd by the Salley which the Enemy made the day before, and to rebuild the Gallery which they had burn'd, ſo that they deſign'd to put the Miners to work that evening. On the <hi>Bavarian</hi> ſide the Miners were ſet to work under the Paliſado of the Roundel, and under the Wall, in hopes that the Mines would be ready to ſpring in three days. We had Soldiers kill'd and wounded, among whom thoſe of chiefeſt note were Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Wachtenheim,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in one of the <hi>Suabian</hi> Regiments. At the ſame time we had Intelligence by our Spies that the Turks, to the number of ſeven thouſand, re-inforced by the Tartars that ramble about the Country, had a deſign to put a new Governour into <hi>Buda,</hi> with a Supply of Men; which obliged the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ſome Infantry to poſt themſelves on the other ſide the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naw,</hi> and joyn in caſe of neceſſity with the Cavalry which lay there, and to meet and fight the Enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 11. This night five Demi-Cannon were planted upon the new Batteries in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, and two Mortar Pieces upon a little Fort adjoyning, with the loſs only of two Soldiers ſlain, and five wounded. The <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> planted three Pieces upon a Battery, and the next night they planted a greater number to ſhoot red hot Bullets into the City. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> likewiſe ſecured their Works with two Redoubts. Yeſterday in the evening four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred commanded Foot were ſent upon <hi>Peſt</hi> ſide to raiſe ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences upon the <hi>Danaw</hi> to prevent the putting of any Relief into <hi>Buda.</hi> And now the Command of Lieutenant Colonel to <hi>Souches</hi> being vacant by the death of the Sieur <hi>Fonck,</hi> who dy'd yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of his wound in the Leg, it was conferred upon the Count of <hi>Herlerſtein,</hi> Serjeant Major to <hi>La Vergne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 12. All the Batteries were finiſhed, as well in the <hi>Lorrain</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98375:15"/>Attack, as in that of the <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> and the firſt Lines of theſe two Attacks were joyned in ſuch a manner, that the men might paſs from the one to the other ſecure from the Shot of the Enemy. For being ſo near the Wall as they were, the Beſieged did nothing but throw Granado's, and ſling Stones, to diſturb the Workmen: But being thus ſecured, the damage they did us was inconſiderable. The Miners in the Mine on the Lefthand, were already far advanced under the Wall: But in that upon the Right-hand they met with more difficulty, and therefore they reſolved to widen the Breach with their Cannon. Laſt Night the Count <hi>de Souches,</hi> who commanded in the Trenches, cauſed the Breach to be viewed by the Orders of Count <hi>Starenbergh,</hi> and it was found wide enough to make an Aſſault. The <hi>Brandenburgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> alſo this day began to ſhoot red-hot Bullets and Bombs into the City, with twenty two Cannons and two Mortar-Pieces; but they did no great Execution, in regard the Beſieged had taken away all the Rafters of their Houſes. And yet the Bombs and Carcaſſes invented by the Franciſcan Fryer, and the Spaniſh En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineer, may be ſaid to work Wonders. Nevertheleſs the main buſineſs of this day was to widen and level the Breaches; and we had this day nine wounded and three killed, by the Granado's and Stones. As for the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> the Breach which they had made in the great Roundel was by this time wide enough, and the Miners were at work under the Paliſado of the Trench. Ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having Intelligence that the Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier was advanced with ſome thouſand <hi>Turks</hi> as far as <hi>Hatwan,</hi> commanded Three thouſand Horſe, and ſix Battalions of Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>Imperialiſts, Bavarians,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of General Baron <hi>de Mercy,</hi> to paſs the <hi>Danaw,</hi> and poſt themſelves on the other ſide of the Bridge, to prevent the Enemy from putting any Relief into the Town, with a new Governor, called <hi>Achmet Baſſa,</hi> reputed one of the beſt Officers that the <hi>Turk</hi> has in his Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 13. This morning the Enemy ſprung a Mine at the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Roundel near to ours, that was already finiſhed, without ſo much as the loſs of one Man of our ſide: Tho on the other ſide it did the Execution which ours ought to have done, and overthrew a part of the Roundel, where as yet we had not made any Breach. There were two hundred <hi>Turks</hi> who were ready to have fallen pell mell into our Works ſo ſoon as the Mine was ſprung; but finding it had done an Execution quite contrary to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98375:16"/>what they expected, they retir'd. And now all things being in a Readineſs for an Aſſault, to the end they might poſt themſelves upon the Wall; Count <hi>Starenbergh</hi> directed the Attack in the following manner. Count <hi>Guido Starenbergh,</hi> Lieutenant Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel to the Regiment of that Name, was commanded upon the right hand againſt the Roundel: Count <hi>de Herberſteen,</hi> Serjeant Major to <hi>Scherffenbergh</hi> was in the middle of the Curtin, and the Count <hi>d' Averſpergh</hi> Lieutenant Collonel to <hi>Mansfield</hi> had the left hand. They had each two hundred and eighty Soldiers: The Engineers, Granadeers, Fuſeleers, Carpenters, and Pioneers, were poſted between them and the reſt, to the number of two thouſand men were divided into three Bodies of Reſerve, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and relieve the Aſſailants. The Volunteers, who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted that Station, intermixed themſelves among the firſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſeven and eight of the Clock in the Evening the Signal was given to mount the Breaches, with a Peal from all the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, and a ſhowre of Bombs and Carcaſſes that were ſhot againſt the City and the Retrenchments of the Enemy behind the breach. Nor could all the Reſiſtance of the Enemy prevent our men from mounting, where the combat was very obſtinate on both ſides, and maintained for the ſpace of three quarters of an Hour with all the bravery imaginable: At what time the Enemy alſo ſprang a Mine under our firſt Line, which buried Captain <hi>Kalkreiter</hi> of <hi>Starenbergh</hi>'s Regiment, and ſome Soldiers. But at length, finding we could not get footing for want of Ground, that we could not force the Palliſado'd Retrenchment of the Beſieged behind the Breach, and that our chief Officers were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready all either wounded or killed by the continual firing of the Enemy, it was thought convenient to cauſe the Aſſailants to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, who had fought like Lions, and of which five were ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant as to throw themſelves into the Retrenchment, and yet to bring themſelves off and retire with the reſt; who, had they been but duly ſuccoured, perhaps there would have needed no farther work to have lodged upon the Breach. However the Retreat was made in good Order. The Regiments of <hi>Souches</hi> and <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſuffered moſt in this Action; and <hi>Starenbergh</hi>'s alſo was very much damnified. There were about four hundred killed and wounded: but that which was more particularly to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored, was the loſs of ſo many brave Officers and Volunteers. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and Camp-Marſhal-General <hi>Starenbergh</hi> were preſent at this Action, giving Orders every where as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98375:16"/>required. Few of the wounded eſcaped, which is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſome believe the Turks do ſhoot with poyſon'd Bullets. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the dead were the Count <hi>de Herberſtein</hi> Serjeant Major to <hi>Scherffenbergh,</hi> the Count of <hi>Kuffſtein,</hi> a Captain to <hi>Starembergh,</hi> with another Captain of the ſame Regiment. The Baron of <hi>Rolle,</hi> the <hi>Sieur Kirchmeyer,</hi> one of <hi>Souches</hi>'s Captains; and two of <hi>Mansfield</hi>'s Captains, with eight Enſigns and Lieutenants of Infantry. Of the Volunteers that were ſlain or died of their Wounds, the chief were the Duke of <hi>Vejar,</hi> Grandee of <hi>Spain,</hi> who behaved himſelf with ſo much Courage that he was one of the firſt upon the Breach. Prince <hi>Robert</hi>'s Son, with another Engliſh Lord, the Baron of <hi>Scheyffer,</hi> the Son of the Count of <hi>Maldegem,</hi> the young Count of <hi>Courmaillon,</hi> a Count of <hi>Donaw,</hi> and ſeven or eight other Perſons of Quality. Among the wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well Officers as Volunteers, there was Lieutenant-Collonel <hi>Guido de Starenbergh</hi> wounded with the ſplinter of a Granado in the Shoulder, and a Musket Bullet in the Foot, Lieutenant Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel the Count <hi>d' Averſpergh</hi> in the Foot, but not dangerouſly; and indeed there were few of the reſt of the Officers eſcaped; the Prince of <hi>Veldens,</hi> of the <hi>Palatine</hi> Family, Prince <hi>Picolomine,</hi> two Engliſh Lords, the Duke of <hi>Eſcalona,</hi> a Grandee of <hi>Spain;</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Valero,</hi> Brother to the Duke of <hi>Vejar;</hi> the Prince of <hi>Commercy,</hi> and above thirty other Volunteers of Quality. The Spaniſh and Engliſh diſtinguiſhed themſelves, and fighting to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vye one another, endured the main Fury of the Enemy. And indeed the Engliſh ſuffered very much: For of twenty, all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality, there were not above ſix that were not either killed or wounded. The Loſs of the Beſieged was alſo very great, for by what we underſtood afterwards, they had above two hundred of their chiefeſt Men killed and wounded. It was thought the <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburghers</hi> would have made an Attempt on their ſide, but they excuſed themſelves, alledging that their Breach was not then wide enough. However the Turks upon the Retreat of our Men, made a little ſally upon their Attack; but were repulſed with the loſs of twenty four of their Party. Upon the <hi>Bavarian</hi> ſide they had made a conſiderable Breach in the Roundel, and in the Wall that ſecures the Caſtle, which the Beſieged repair'd every Night with Gabions, Paliſado's, and Bavins.</p>
            <p>The 14th. All the night and day was ſpent in burying the dead and repairing the Approaches, in planting more Cannon upon the Batteries, and in carrying on the Mines, the Miners being actually
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98375:17"/>ſet to work under Ground on the ſide of the great Roundel. Two Galleries were alſo built toward the Curtin, between the twelfth and thirteenth Roundel. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> alſo having ſent for three Regiments of Horſe from near <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> to go and re-inforce General <hi>Mercy,</hi> the Count <hi>de Caprara</hi> detach'd the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of <hi>Truſches, Taff,</hi> and <hi>Stirum,</hi> who this morning paſs'd the Bridge on <hi>Peſt</hi> ſide. In the evening the beſieged ſprung a Mine in the <hi>Eavarian</hi> Attack, on the left hand of the Roundel of the Caſtle, which ſucceeded very ill. The ſame day his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral Highneſs having caus'd eight Parapets of thick oaken Planks plaited with Iron, (being a new Invention, found them very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per) to be made uſe of in Aſſaults and Attacks, every Parapet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufficient to ſecure a hundred armed men. The ſame day the <hi>Bavarians</hi> diſcovered and diſappointed five Mines of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>The 15th. They went on finiſhing their Lines, and being to dig under the Wall, they heard the Enemy at work under the breach. This day the Sieur <hi>Gonzales</hi> arriv'd, and ſhot his Bombs and Carcaſſes into the City, which did great Execution, where five or ſix were kill'd and wounded. This day the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving intelligence that the Convoy of the Enemy which had paſs'd the <hi>Tibiſcus</hi> near <hi>Segedin,</hi> lay ſtill encamp'd under the Cannon of the Fortreſs of <hi>Hatwan,</hi> his Excellency ſent for two Regiments of Horſe more to joyn with General <hi>Mercy,</hi> with a deſign to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the Enemy to repaſs the River.</p>
            <p>On the 16th a new Battery was erected in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack without the Wall of the low Town on the right hand, againſt the great Roundel, which was alſo battered on the other ſide to make the breach the larger. This day a <hi>Raſcian</hi> coming out of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with a Packet of Letters which the Governor of the place had intruſted him with, to carry to the Governour of <hi>Alba Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> rendred himſelf in the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s Quarters. But in regard the Letters were written in the <hi>Armenian</hi> Language, and for that there was never an Interpreter in the Camp, they ſent them to <hi>Vienna</hi> to be deciphered. Some Country People alſo making their Eſcape from the Town, reported that the <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries</hi> began to murmur againſt the Governour for being ſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to let things go to the utmoſt extremity; but that by the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Mutineers, by means of his Money, and a ſtrong aſſurance of ſpeedy Succour, he had ſo well confirm'd the reſt in their duty, that they promiſed to hold out to the laſt drop of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98375:17"/>blood. This evening the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> commanded a hundred and fifty men, ſeconded by a great number, to attack the Paliſado in the Trench at the foot of the Roundel of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, the Lieutenant General the Count of <hi>Fontain,</hi> undertook the Attack on the right hand, and the Count of <hi>Aſpremont</hi> on the left. And this was the firſt time they made uſe of three Parapets of Wood, which were very profitable to us; and they attackt that poſt ſo vigorouſly, that they carried it by dint of Sword, and cut to pieces all that were in it; but they ſold their Lives dear however, for we had there the Count of <hi>Fontain</hi> kill'd, with five and thirty Soldiers and Volunteers. The Count of <hi>Aſpremont</hi> was very much bruis'd in the Head with a Musket-bullet, which ſtrook off his Steel-cap. Baron <hi>Gottalisky</hi> Captain of <hi>Beck</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Sieur <hi>Vaubon</hi> Captain of the Granadeers of <hi>Baden,</hi> were both dangerouſly wounded, with ſeveral others. However this Poſt gave us acceſs to the Roundel.</p>
            <p>The 17. Yeſterday the Enemy began to ſhoot from a new Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of four great Pieces which they had raiſed within the inner Wall; but General <hi>Starenbergh,</hi> giving order to the Gunners to play upon it with ſeveral Pieces, they ſo utterly deſtroyed that Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery in a ſhort time, that the beſieged could make no farther uſe of it. About noon twenty or thirty <hi>Janiſaries</hi> ſhew'd themſelves upon the breach of the Roundel on the right hand, but the Soldiers from the Trenches firing upon 'em, they retired immediately. The Prince of <hi>Croy</hi> arrived in the Camp yeſterday in the evening, with Commiſſion to be General of the Artillery. This day <hi>Capra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi>'s and <hi>Newburgh</hi>'s Regiment of Horſe marched to joyn General <hi>Mercy.</hi> As for the <hi>Bavarians</hi> and <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> they did little this day but mind the finiſhing of their Works, and fired conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually from their Batteries.</p>
            <p>The 18. We advanced ſome Paces with a new Line to the right, the better to protect our Miners that wrought in two diſtinct places under the Curtin, and to make uſe of it in the next Aſſault. The <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> enlarged their great Battery of three Pieces of Cannon. Nor were the <hi>Bavarians</hi> idle, for their Miners were at work under the Wall behind the Palliaſado'd Trench, of which they had made themſelves Maſters. As for the Enemy, he ſeldom now appear'd in the day time; but in the night time they kept ſiring continually, and kill'd us a great many men, with their Stones and Granadoes, which they flung into our Works.</p>
            <p>The 19. The Cannon was planted upon the new Battery, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98375:18"/>the Line was ſecured with two little Forts. Laſt night the Enemy ſprang a Mine behind our Miners that wrought under the Wall, which damnified our Mine, into which there was a neceſſity to make a new Entrance, to make it ſerviceable again. Some of our Miners were almoſt buried in the Earth, but they were all fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately recovered again, except the Sieur <hi>Libert</hi> their Captain, whoſe Body could not not be found. Mr. <hi>Kerry,</hi> Brother to my Lord <hi>Ouberry,</hi> a Scotch Lord was kill'd in the Approaches with a Musket bullet, together with ſeven or eight Soldiers, and ſome wounded. This morning the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> held a Council of War, where were preſent the Generals of his Army; but the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination was kept ſecret. Some Deſerters alſo came to the Camp this day, and aſſured us that the beſieged would come to no Compoſition, but were reſolved to wait the Relief which the <hi>Grand Viſier</hi> ſhould bring them.</p>
            <p>The 20. The new Line in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack was finiſhed. Three falſe Alarms alſo were given to the beſieged only to harraſs them, by cauſing certain Granadeers to mount the Breach, who threw Granadoes into the Place, upon which the <hi>Turks</hi> haſtning to make defence, were ſaluted with ſeveral Cannon-ſhot, Bombs and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſes that did good Execution. Which ſort of Attacks were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, to keep the Enemy in continual Alarm, and in ignorance of the time of the really deſign'd Aſſault. Moreover, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſloy carried on their Mines; a certain <hi>German</hi> undertaking a new one, which he promiſed to finiſh in two or three days. In the <hi>Bavarian</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> Attacks there was nothing paſs'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, only that the Miners hop'd the next night to be under the Roundels. They alſo continued battering the Walls with great fury, and ſhoting red hot Bullets, Bombs, and Carcaſſes into the City, which did very much miſchief. Upon Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given that the <hi>Turks</hi> prepared to relieve the place, the Trench of the Line of Circumvallation was made deeper; and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with certain Redoubts, the better to ſecure the beſiegers; to which purpoſe two hundred <hi>Heydukes</hi> were added to the number of Pioneers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 21. The principal Work now carried on was that of the Mines, which were opened in three ſeveral parts. Nor could Captain <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>'s body yet be found, though all diligence has been uſed to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llow the Earth in that place where his body was by all conjecture loſt. He was an Officer, a <hi>Walloon</hi> by Nation, much lamented by all the Generals, and by all that knew his Experience
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98375:18"/>in the buſineſs of Mining: Our Miners alſo heard the Enemy at work, but they went on with their own work for all that. A Battery was likewiſe raiſed for four Mortar Pieces, near that of the three Spaniſh Pieces, which batter the Roundel on the right Hand. Moreover all the Cannons and Mortar Pieces were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to be planted nearer the Breaches, on purpoſe to widen them with more eaſe, and ruin the Defences of the Enemy, which are behind the ſaid Breaches: We had in the Lorrain Attack only twenty ſeven killed and wounded, among whom were Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant Major <hi>Boeneburgh,</hi> a <hi>Dane,</hi> and the <hi>Sieur Lerneux,</hi> the fifth Captain of <hi>Starenbergh</hi>'s Regiment. The <hi>Sieur Gonzale</hi>'s Bombs and Carcaſſes have had the ſucceſs which was expected; For by the Report of a Deſerter, one of thoſe Bombs falling yeſterday into the City, made its way into a Houſe, into which were retired above a Hundred Perſons of both Sexes, who were all miſerably buried in the Ruins of it. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> finiſhed their Battery near the Roundel, and began another toward the water ſide, to batter the Flanks of the City on that ſide. And now the three Attacks having made their Approaches to the Breaches that now ſeem'd wide enough, all things were preparing for a general Aſſault, there being two thouſand ſcaling Ladders in a readineſs to make falſe Attacks and ſcale the Walls, while others mounted the Breaches.</p>
            <p>The 22. Nothing paſſed conſiderable in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, nor in that of the <hi>Brandenburgher:</hi> but the Enemy this morning ſprang two Mines, which did no other Execution than only ruin a part of the Curtin, where there was no Breach before. The new Battery likewiſe of four pieces upon the brink of the Ditch of the Roundel being finiſhed, the Turks gave 'em a moſt bloody Serenade by break of day; for ſallying out in a good number, they ſtole down into the Trench along the Paliſade, and being come to the ſaid Battery before they were diſcovered, through the darkneſs of the Night, they ſet up a moſt dreadful How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Hollowing, nayl'd three pieces of Cannon and a Mortar, and ruined ſome part of the Gabions of the Battery: The <hi>Saxons</hi> of the adjoining Poſts haſtning to the Relief of their Friends, were put into ſome Diſorder; but Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Badens</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, being the Reſerve, coming up in time, repelled the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my with the loſs of thirty men ſtain. Which was but a ſmall thing in compariſon of the Loſs which we ſuffered, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to above a hundred killed and wounded, the moſt part
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98375:19"/>
               <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Bavarians.</hi> Among the ſlain were Collonel <hi>Lehel</hi> of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Forces, and ſome inferiour Officers: The Sieur <hi>Geſch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wint,</hi> Collonel of the Artillery, was alſo dangerouſly gaſhed and hack'd with a Scimiter. However the <hi>Turks</hi> got no advantage by this Salley; for the Nails being eaſily pull'd out of the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non and Mortar, within an hour after they began to play a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as if they had never been nail'd. And the revenge which they returned was ſpeedy; for one of the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Bombs light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Magazin of Powder in the Caſtle, the whole Pile blew up into the Air with ſuch a hideous havock and thundring noiſe, as not only ſhook the whole City, but our Camp likewiſe; and by what we afterwards underſtood from the Deſerters, there miſerably periſhed by that blow above a thouſand perſons of all Ages, which were buried in the Ruins of the Buildings, the Stones of which were thrown with that violence and vaſt quantity into the Approaches, that they reſembled a ſhowr of Hail, and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeveral of the Soldiers.</p>
            <p>The 23. the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent in the Afternoon the Count of <hi>Conningſegg</hi> with an Interpreter to the beſieged, with a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to ſurrender, in regard all the Mines were ready to ſpring, and all things were prepared for a general Aſſault: During which time there was a Ceſſation of Arms on both ſides, which was ſpent in the Interment of the ſlain. The ſaid Count, after he had been two hours in the City, returned to the Camp with a Letter from <hi>Abdi Baſſa</hi> in a Purſe of red Damask, which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> wherein the <hi>Baſſa</hi> made him a haughty and arrogant Anſwer, purporting, That not being neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to a Surrender, he could not dream of ſuch a vile piece of Cowardice: that he fought for the Glory of his <hi>Prophet,</hi> and the Honour of the <hi>Muſſel-men:</hi> that he and his Garriſon were reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to hold out to the utmoſt Extremty, and defend it to the laſt gaſp of Breath: that the place being intruſted to his care by the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> he would preſerve it, or loſe his Life: that when the Duke ſhould come to wreſt it from him, he ſhould find him upon the Breach ready to diſpute his Entrance; and let him order the Aſſault when he pleaſed, he would expect him without ſtirring afoot.</p>
            <p>The Duke having read this inſolent Anſwer, cauſed all the Batteries to fire with greater fury than before, and cauſed all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations to be haſtened to give a general Aſſault by break of day; to which purpoſe he ſent for a thouſand <hi>Hungarian</hi> Foot,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98375:19"/>who had voluntarily offered themſelves to mount the Breaches.</p>
            <p>So haughty an Anſwer, and a Defence of the beſieged ſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and brave, ſhews us by Experience that the Characters which the Deſerters had given us at the beginning of the Siege, of <hi>Abdi Baſſa</hi>'s conduct, were utterly falſe, in ſaying he was contemptible to the Soldiery for being more a Merchant than a Soldier; and the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> was to blame in going about to diſplace him as he had deſigned: for it is to be preſumed that hardly any other than he, would have ſo long eluded the Fury of ſuch a Potent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p>This day ſome <hi>Bavarians,</hi> that kept the advanced Guards, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving that a <hi>Polonian,</hi> who ſerved in our Army, had had a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conference with two <hi>Turks,</hi> ſeized upon him at his return to the Camp, and carried him to the Elector, where having been ſearched and examined, he was found to be a Spy, and that he had diſcovered to the Enemies all that had paſſed in our Camp; whereupon he was preſently ſentenced and executed without any more ado. This evening alſo a <hi>Bavarian</hi> Cannoneer was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, who was going over to the Enemy, and had already paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Guards.</p>
            <p>The 24. This morning, about eight of the Clock, a large Mine was ſprung in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, and three hundred choſen Foot were ordered out to lodg themſelves upon the Breach, together with ſome hundreds of <hi>Hungarians:</hi> but the effect of the Mine was contrary to all expectation; for it ruined and overthrew a part of our Approaches, and filled our Lines with Earth, beſides that we had a hundred men killed and wounded. Whereupon his Serene Highneſs ſeeing this ill Succeſs, ordered the Batteries to redouble their firing to inlarge their Bteaches, and to reduce them to ſuch a Condition, as to be mounted without making any Mines. The new Battery of the <hi>Bavarians</hi> toward the water ſide was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed this night; and that other which they had raiſed on the ſide of the Ditch, had already broken down a good part of the Wall on the right hand.</p>
            <p>The ſame day the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent Orders to the Count of <hi>Nigrelli,</hi> who commanded in <hi>Newhauſel</hi> during the abſence of the Count of <hi>Aſpremont,</hi> to come to the Army and officiate the place of General of Battalia: by intercepted Letters alſo he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> encouraged the beſieged to defend themſelves, promiſing that by the eighth or tenth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> at the fartheſt, he would come and relieve them with a formidable
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98375:20"/>Army. The ſame day likewiſe General <hi>Caprara,</hi> who commands the Body of the Imperial Forces upon the River <hi>Tibiſcus,</hi> ſent an Officer to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> to give them the news of a great Advantage which he had gained upon the Garriſon of <hi>Agria</hi> the fifteenth of this Month, by the means of two Ambuſcadoes which he laid for the <hi>Turks;</hi> into which having drawn ſix hundred of thoſe Barbarians, he utterly defeated 'em, kill'd three hundred upon the place, together with <hi>Oſman Baſha</hi> the Governour of <hi>Agria;</hi> and taken ninety Priſoners, among whom he found the <hi>Vice-Baſha</hi> dangeroully wounded: and that in this Action General <hi>Heuſler</hi> had behaved himſelf with his wonted Gallantry, as had alſo done the Sieurs <hi>Pecerhaſi</hi> and <hi>Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> with their <hi>Hungarians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 25. Nothing was done but only carrying on the Reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Works ruined by the Mine which was ſprung the day before to our diſadvantage. The Duke of <hi>Loarrin</hi> haſtened with all the vigour imaginable the preparations for a general Aſſault, having ordered the making ſuch parading places as were neceſſary within the Lines and Approaches: and the <hi>Bavarians</hi> and <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburghers</hi> did the like in their Quarters. Between four and five in the afternoon the beſieged ſet fire to a little Mine on the right hand of the Roundel; which done, they ſallied forth with two hundred foot, who were as ſoon repulſed by our men that were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Guard. The Enemy left fourteen behind them ſlain, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſome wounded along with 'em: A while after they ſalli'd out with a greater number upon the <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> who repelled 'em with the ſame eaſe: Not long after they returned with a greater number, and put the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> Guards into ſome diſorder, which obliged the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to order the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that lay poſted at the VVall of the low Town, to advance; which General <hi>Souches,</hi> who commanded the Trenches, divided into three parts; of which one was planted one on the left hand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the water ſide; the other entred the Approaches; and the third was ordered to ſtand firm near the <hi>Moſque.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ordered the Battalions of <hi>Mansfield, Salm, Souches,</hi> to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance on the right hand. The Skirmiſh continued ſome time, and the Turks retreated ſeveral times, then made Head again, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Air with their barbarous Cries. The <hi>Heydukes,</hi> after the firſt diſcharge, encountred the <hi>Turks,</hi> but gave ground, and caus'd ſome confuſion among ours that advanc'd upon the left of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Moſque,</hi> whence the beſieged fired with their Cannon, yet
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98375:20"/>without doing any conſiderable damage: ſo that the Enemy ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they could gain nothing but blows, retired into the City. Count <hi>Starenburgh</hi> ſignalized himſelf in this Action, giving all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Orders to our men; but his <hi>Adjutant</hi> had both his Legs carried away by a Cannon ſhot. The Battalions of <hi>Souches</hi> and <hi>Mansfield</hi> were but courſely handled, of whom many were ſlain. The Baron <hi>d' Aſti</hi> was wounded in the Foot, the Baron of <hi>Hoben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warth</hi> ſlain, and ſome inferiour Officers were likewiſe kill'd and wounded, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>out an hundred common Soldiers. But the loſs of the <hi>Tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was much more conſiderable, as we underſtood by a <hi>German</hi> boy who made his eſcape out of the City, where he had been ever ſince the <hi>Turks</hi> were beaten from <hi>Vienna,</hi> by whom he had been taken and ſold to an Inhabitant of <hi>Buda.</hi> This boy reported that the <hi>Turks</hi> made great Intrenchments within the Town, and that the Gariſon was ſtill five thouſand fighting men. In the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack there was nothing paſſed conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>The 26. During the whole Siege never was more diligence uſed in carrying on to perfection the Lines and Approaches than laſt night, and all this, as alſo for the making of Parading Places, which were by this time finiſhed, and every thing prepared for a general Aſſault, and to lodg themſelves upon the breaches of the Roun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels and Walls, ſo that at length we might make our ſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of that Important Place that had already coſt us ſo much blood. This day likewiſe the beſieged made a ſlight ſalley upon the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> Quarters, which proved to their diſadvantage; for they were conſtrained, after they had ſtood the firſt Charge, to retreat back to the City faſter than they came.</p>
            <p>The 27. All things being ready at length for a general Aſſault, and the Companies that were to ſerve in this Action being drawn up in their ſeveral Parading Places, as well in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack as in thoſe of the <hi>Bavarian</hi> and <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> it was reſolved that the Onſet ſhould be given about five in the Evening, to which purpoſe the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had given out his Orders to all the Officers, both Superiour and Inferiour, what they were to do. The Faggots, Gabions, Spades, Pickaxes, Hatchets, and Sacks of Earth were all in a readineſs, as well to dig down the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments of the Enemies, as for the Defence of the Aſſailants, when they ſhould be Maſters of the Breach. The Signal was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from <hi>Peſt,</hi> by the diſcharge of ſome great Guns; and the Aſſault was managed after the following manner. Forty Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deers
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98375:21"/>under a Captain Lieutenant and Serjeant, were placed firſt at the head of the Right-hand-Roundel, they were followed by fifty Fuſeleers, and fifty Souldiers with Hatchets, under a Captain Lieutenant, and Serjeant. Theſe were firſt to mount the Breach and drive away the Enemy. A Captain, a Lieutenant, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant, with a hundred men carrying Spades and Pickaxes, made the firſt Line, ſeconded by two Captains, two Lieutenants, and two Serjeants, with two hundred Muſqueteers, the whole under the Prince of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> grand Maſter of the Teutonick Order, who had the management of this Attack. That of the middle, toward the Curtin was under the Direction of Lieutenant-General <hi>Souches;</hi> to carry on that, were fifty Granadeers under a Captain, a Lieutenant, and a Serjeant. One hundred Fuſeleers under a Captain, a Lieutenant, and a Serjeant; and to ſecond theſe there were two Captains, two Lieutenants, and two Serjeants, with two hundred Muſqueteers, divided into two ſquadrons, followed by a hundred men with Shovels and Pickaxes.</p>
            <p>The Attack on the left hand of the little Roundel was ordered by the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> after the following manner.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond Line behind the ſacks fill'd with Earth, Wool, and ſuch like materials, were poſted the Arquebuſiers, made choice of upon this occaſion, who were not to ſtir, but to fire continually upon the Turks that ſhould ſhew themſelves upon the Breaches. The <hi>Heydukes,</hi> commanded by the Deputy-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Raab,</hi> were poſted toward the Water-ſide, where a great part of the Wall was thrown down by the Fire which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the Magazine, which had been blown up ſome days before. They were only to make a falſe Attack, and were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by a Serjeant Major, with ſome ſelect Companies. The ſuperior Officers poſſeſſed ſeveral Poſts to do the Duty of their Employments. To which purpoſe the Marqueſs of <hi>Nigrelli,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of Battalia, Collonel <hi>Keth,</hi> and the Baron <hi>de Rederer,</hi> and the Serjeant-Major of <hi>Starenbergh</hi> ſtood by the grand Maſter of the Teutonic Order. Lieutenant-General <hi>Souches</hi> had for his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants Baron <hi>Diependael,</hi> General of Battalia, the Count <hi>D'Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinghen,</hi> Collonel, Lieutenant-Collonel <hi>Jonger,</hi> and the Serjeant-Major to <hi>Croy.</hi> There were above twelve hundred men for a Reſerve in the cloſe way, commanded by the General of Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia <hi>Thungen,</hi> under twelve Captains, twelve Lieutenants, and other inferior Officers, with all the Lieutenant-Collonels, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant-Majors to ſucceed in the Places of thoſe that ſhould be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98375:21"/>kill'd or wounded. Which twelve hundred Muſqueteers were to advance in little Bodies in the Lines as the others gained ground. The reſt of the Infantry ſtood to their Arms ready to fight, and the Generals in the Trenches.</p>
            <p>In this Order, the Soldiers full of Courage and Gallantry, went to the Aſſault, and mounted the Breaches, where they ſound great Reſiſtance, eſpecially at the great Roundel, where the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to the Breach was high, and the Defendants numerous and well reſolv'd. Ours were two or three times repulſed, yet every time renewing the Aſſault, at length they made themſelves ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Breach, and made good their Poſts. The <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burghers</hi> got Poſſeſſion of the little Wall, among whom were fifty <hi>Heydukes</hi> that behaved themſelves very well. The Fight laſted from five till nine at Night, with great Effuſion of Blood, not ſo much by the Enemies Weapons as by their Mines, and the Powder which they had ſtrew'd in ſeveral places, to which they ſtill ſet Fire as they were driven from their Poſts. There could be nothing more lamentable than to ſee between two or three hundred men at a time blown up into the Air by the force of their Mines, who were partly killed, and partly deſperately wounded. Yet for all this the Enemy could not terrify our men, nor by their obſtinate Reſiſtance prevent 'em from lodging upon the Roundels, and upon the Curtin. There was no great good done by the <hi>Heydukes</hi> that were with the Imperialiſts, for they were greatly afraid of Fire, and that Fear diſcourag'd 'em from making the falſe Attack toward the Water Side. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and Count <hi>de Starenbergh,</hi> ſtood near the grand Maſter of the Teutonic Order, with their Swords in their Hands, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the Officers and Soldiers to do their Duty. The Prince of <hi>Croy</hi> ſtood in the middle near the Curtin, where he was wounded.</p>
            <p>Night parting the Combat, they finiſhed their Lodgments with two Lines of Communication of the Approaches to the Roundels poſſeſſed; and they put the Miners to Work at the Wall or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment within, where the <hi>Turks</hi> fortified themſelves. We cannot ſufficiently applaud the martial Valour of the Generals, Officers and Soldiers that were in this piece of Service, who were almoſt all wounded, in ſight of the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> whoſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutant General, the <hi>Steur d' Artein,</hi> was ſlain as he was carrying Orders. The number of the Slain was not very great, but that of the wounded extraordinary; among whom were the Prince of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98375:22"/>
               <hi>Croy,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Commercy,</hi> General <hi>Diependale,</hi> General <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> the Baron of <hi>Aſti,</hi> who notwitſtanding he was wounded but two days before, would needs ſignalize himſelf in this Action, where he received a ſecond wound, the Serjeant-Major of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> two Captains of the ſame Regiment, the Baron of <hi>Redere,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel of the Regiment of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> Serjeant Major <hi>Pini,</hi> Count <hi>Schlick,</hi> Baron <hi>Gera,</hi> and ſeveral other Captains; Lieutenants, and other inferior Officers. On the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> ſide, Count <hi>Donaw,</hi> Colonel of Foot, was Slain, as alſo the <hi>Sieur Marwitz,</hi> Serjeant-major, and the Prince of <hi>Curland</hi> grievouſly wounded; with ſeveral others.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack, the Elector had ordered the Onſet in this manner. The Paliſado's upon the Breach-being burnt the day before by forty ſelected Soldiers, his Electoral Highneſs command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Lieutenant with twenty Fuſeleers, a Serjeant with ſix Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunteers and ten Granadeers, a Corporal with ſix Carpenters, to cut the Palliſado's: A hundred Muſqueteers under a Captain and two Lieutenants, had Orders to Poſt themſelves at the Enemies Palliſado's, and to Fire continually, the better to ſecure the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to make a Lodgment upon the Roundel, among which there were twenty five with Shovels and Pickaxes, and ſeventy five with Hatchets under a Captain; all which were guarded by a Leiute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-Collonel, a Serjeant-Major; and a Captain, with fifty men arm'd with Half-pikes, Halberds and Partiſans, a Lieutenant with thirty Granadeers, and two hundred Muſqueteers under two Captains and two Lieutenants. This Order being obſerved as well upon the right Hand as upon the left, the two adjoyning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubts were finiſhed with thirty Arquebuſiers each, and three Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talions of Imperialiſts, <hi>Bavarians</hi> and <hi>Saxons,</hi> were to ſecond the Aſſailants. The Cannoneers and Bombardeers had order to Fire from all the Batteries, and to throw Bombs and Carcaſſes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion, into the Caſtle, and between the two firſt Walls towards the Water-ſide.</p>
            <p>All things thus ordered, they advanced through the Overtures toward the Breach (tho very high and difficult to aſcend) on the right and left Hand of the Roundel, as alſo of the Curtin, and with that Fury, that they made themſelves maſters of the Poſt, and drave away the Enemy, notwithſtanding their continual firing their Muskets, and a ſhowre of Stones, which they threw from the Windows of the Caſtle. They alſo made themſelves maſters of the <hi>Swinger,</hi> which is a great ſpace of Ground in form of a Retreating
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98375:22"/>Place, between the Wall and the Houſes. But this place being commanded by the higher Walls, from which the Enemy did much endamage our men with their Granadoes, Stones, and Bombs, his Electoral Highneſs cauſed thoſe that had the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it to retire, thinking it ſufficient to ſecure their Lodgments upon the Roundel and the Wall of the Caſtle, with a Line of Communication from the Gate of the Bridge to the <hi>Swinger-Gate;</hi> to the end they might have the Bridge in their own power; to which purpoſe they alſo raiſed tranſverſe Lines, and two Redoubts. His Electoral Highneſs ſhewed himſelf all the while on the firſt Poſts, encouraging his men with his preſence. All the Generals ſignalized their Courage by ſtriving to outvie one another, as did alſo the Officers, Volunteers and Soldiers, who fought with all the bravery that could be expected from men of Courage. The <hi>Turks</hi> who defended the Caſtle and <hi>Swinger,</hi> were for the moſt part kill'd and wounded, only ſome few that ſaved themſelves by flight. There were found eight pieces of Cannon, and two Mortar Pieces, which were made uſe of to batter the ſecond Wall, or the Enemies Parapet within the City. In this Aſſault of the <hi>Bavurians</hi> were killed two Lieutenants of the Regiment of <hi>Baden,</hi> and five Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, one Lieutenant, and three Enſigns wounded. Of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of <hi>Beck,</hi> the Baron of <hi>Welsbergh,</hi> Lieutenant Collonel, five Captains, three Lieutenants, and five Enſigns wounded. Of the Regiment of <hi>Aſpremont,</hi> the Collonel, Lieutenant Collonel, Count <hi>Nicholas Palfi,</hi> Serjeant Major Count <hi>Zacco,</hi> ſeven Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, five Lieutenants, and two Enſigns wounded, and one En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign killed. Of the Regiment of <hi>Furſtenbergh,</hi> one Captain, one Lieutenant, and one Enſign wounded. In the Elector's Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Guards, one Captain killed, the Serjeant-Major, one Captain and three Lieutenants wounded. In the Regiment of <hi>Steinau,</hi> the Serjeant-Major and one Lieutenant ſlain, one Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, two Lieutenants, and one Enſign wounded. In the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Rummel,</hi> one Captain, and one Lieutenant killed; three Captains and one Enſign wounded. In the Regiment of <hi>Seibolſtorfe,</hi> the Serjeant Major ſlain, one Captain and two Lieutenants wounded. In the Regiment of <hi>Gallenfels,</hi> the Lieutenant Collonel killed, two Captains and one Lieutenant wounded. The Generals, <hi>La Vergne, Rummel</hi> and <hi>Aſprement,</hi> are in the number of the wounded; as alſo the Duke of <hi>Eſcalona,</hi> a Grandee of <hi>Spain;</hi> and ſome other Volunteers of note: In all, what with Officers, what with common Soldiers, One hundred
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98375:23"/>and ſeventeen killed, and Nine hundred ſeventy two wounded. In the <hi>Saxon</hi> Regiments, there was one Lieutenant Collonel, and ſome Inferiour Officers killed, one Lieutenant Collonel, two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant-Majors, two Captains, one Captain Lieutenant, three En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, two Serjeants, and two Corporals wounded: which, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the common Soldiers, made up ſeventy ſlain, and One hundred ninety nine wounded: So that the number of the ſlain and wounded in all the three Attacks, during this vigorous onſet, ſomewhat exceeds three thouſand.</p>
            <p>The 28. There was nothing done in all the three Attacks, their time being ſpent in burying the dead, and ſecuring their Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the breaches. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> alſo cauſed three Mines to be opened under the ſecond Wall in three ſeveral parts, which was alſo done in the <hi>Bavarian</hi> and <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack.</p>
            <p>The 29. About ſeven in the morning three Mines were ſprung under the ſecond Wall, with ſuch ſucceſs, that they made a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble breach in it, and filled up one part of the Trench. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> alſo advanced on the right hand of the Roundel, and made themſelves Maſters of two Mortar Pieces, which they turn'd upon the beſieged. The ſame day the great Cannon were planted nearer to the Town, with a reſolution to batter the inſide of the City with a hundred Pieces of Cannon, and forty Mortar Pieces, if the <hi>Turks</hi> perſiſted in their Obſtinacy: who nevertheleſs went on with their Ditches and Intrenchments behind the Wall with great diligence. And now the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> finding that almoſt all the Generals of the Foot were wounded, and not in a condition to do Service, ordered for the future that two Generals of the Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhould do Duty in the Approaches; <hi>viz.</hi> the Count of <hi>Stirum,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Lodron.</hi> Whereupon the former mounted the Trenches this evening with Lieutenant General <hi>Souches,</hi> and was Relieved the next day by the Grand Maſter of the Teutonic Order, and the Count of <hi>Lodron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 30. A Battery of three Demi-Cannons, and another of four Mortar Pieces, were finiſhed upon the Curtin; and great diligence was uſed to perfect ſeveral Mines, to the end they might be ready for ſpringing the next day. Certain <hi>Raſcians</hi> having made their eſcape out of the Town, reported, That though the beſieged had reſolved to defend themſelves to the laſt; yet that they began to falter in their Reſolutions, and to cry out, That it was but reaſonable to prevent the farther effuſion of blood. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98375:23"/>which a Council of War was held, and after a ſhort Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent a ſecond Summons to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour to Surrender, while there was yet a Door of Mercy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and that he might do it upon honourable Terms; which if he refuſed, he would not be anſwerable for the blood that ſhould be ſpilt, if the Place ſhould be carried by Aſſault, for that the Soldiers would ſpare neither Age nor Sex. <hi>Abdi Baſſa</hi> kindly received his Highneſs's Letter, and deſired a day to conſult with the Officers of his Garriſon, which was granted him; and ſo there was a ſuſpenſion of Arms. The Deſerters that left the Town in great numbers, aſſured us, that in the laſt Aſſault, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack, the <hi>Turks</hi> had three hundred men kill'd, and ſeven hundred wounded. We had Intelligence this evening, that four thouſand Turkiſh Horſe were ſeen four Leagues from the Camp, being ſent to diſcover the Condition of the Place; but that being afraid of being ſurpriz'd, they retreated as ſuddainly.</p>
            <p>The 31. About nine of the clock in the morning the Count of <hi>Lamberg,</hi> Adjutant General, was commanded by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to go with an Interpreter and receive the Governour's Anſwer; which was to this effect: <hi>That he neither could nor would ſo eaſily ſurrender the City which was the Key of the</hi> Ottoman <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; but that if he would make a general Peace, they would ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render into our hands ſome other Town equivalen.</hi> In the afternoon the Enemy deſired a Ceſſation of Arms in the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack, and ſent two <hi>Aga's</hi> in Hoſtage to his Electoral Highneſs, who ſent in their place the Baron of <hi>Creux,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel of the Regiment of <hi>Baden,</hi> with an Interpreter. The <hi>Turks</hi> received him with great Ceremony, and all the Civilities imaginable. However, he was not conducted to the <hi>Baſha,</hi> but into another Houſe, the Streets as he paſſed along being lined with Soldiers in Arms, and in very good order, though not many in number: So ſoon as he came into the Houſe, he was preſented with Rice, a roaſted Pullet, and little Paſties, with Coffee and Wine. The <hi>Baſha</hi> Governour ſent his Excuſe, <hi>That he could not ſpeak with him as yet, until he had conſulted the other Captains of the Garriſon, what Propoſitions to make him.</hi> In which Interval ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Turkiſh Officers came to viſit the Baron. Half an hour after, the Governour ſent word, <hi>That he would take it for a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs if he would be pleaſed to come over to his Houſe;</hi> which the Baron agreed to; and went accompanied with a great number of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98375:24"/>
               <hi>Turks,</hi> of which the two chiefeſt took him under the Arm, and ſo led him before the <hi>Baſha,</hi> who was in a Lodging of Wood over againſt his Houſe, very well adorned, and ſpread with rich Tapeſtries; at which time having cauſed a Seat to be ſet for the Baron, he told him, <hi>That he look'd upon himſelf to be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate to be in ſuch a Place, which had been ſeveral times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged without ſucceſs, and now happened to be ſo long abandoned without Relief. On the other ſide, that he was ſo earneſtly preſt by the Emperour's Son-in-Law, and the Grand Vizier, that he wiſhed he were able to give his Reſolution touching the Surrender of the Place; but that being an Affair of great Importance, and as much as his Life was worth, it was impoſſible for him to reſolve upon Surrender:</hi> adding withal, <hi>That if they would require any other Place in</hi> Hungary, <hi>it ſhould be delivered into the Emperour's hands.</hi> To which the Baron anſwered, <hi>That he had no Commiſſion to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Conditions, but to know of the</hi> Baſha <hi>himſelf, whether he would ſurrender or no: That it behov'd him to conſider that our men were already Maſters of the City: That it would be too late to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulate if he ſtay'd till another Aſſault, when it would not be in the power of the Generals to repreſs the fury of the Soldiers, nor to prevent this Siege from being no leſs Tragical than that of</hi> New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel. To which the <hi>Baſha</hi> made no other Anſwer, but only ſhrugged up his ſhoulders, remaining mute like one that had been Thunder-ſtrook: But as the Baron was going about to depart, he deſird him to go along with him into his Cabinet, whither ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving called the <hi>Muſti,</hi> and three other <hi>Turks</hi> of the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Quality, he declared to him moreover, <hi>That he could not by any means do the Grand Signior ſo great a prejudice as to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render a Place upon which depended two hundred Leagues of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and which was the Key of</hi> Turky; <hi>and then offered again any other City of</hi> Hungary <hi>with its Appendances and Dependencies:</hi> yet at length proteſting farther, <hi>That if he would give him any Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of a general Peace with the Port, that he would then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to ſurrender the City of</hi> Buda. But the Baron, who had no Commiſſion to treat, took leave of the <hi>Baſha,</hi> only telling him, <hi>That he would communicate, both to the Elector and the Duke of</hi> Lorrain, <hi>the Declaration which he had made: but that he could not aſſure him that things would be ſo concluded.</hi> The <hi>Baſha</hi> deſired him to publiſh his Declaration through the Camp in writing, and deſired to be reconducted to the place where he was firſt me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; which was done with a great deal of Ceremony, being accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98375:24"/>by ſeveral of the Turkiſh Officers to the Gate. But it was Impoſible either for the Baron or the Interpreter to expreſs the waſte which our Bombs have made in the City, where they have ruined the greateſt part of the Buildings. The Truce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that had been obſerved during this Inter-parley, was broken off yeſterday in the evening, at what time the great Guns began again to play with greater fury than before.</p>
            <p>This day about Noon the Beſieged ſprang a ſmall Counter-Mine to ruin our Mine made under their Battery oppoſite to the great Roundel, but without any Execution. Two days after we ſprang two of our Mines, which were made to fill up the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which ſucceeded very well: but in the afternoon Count <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renbergh,</hi> looking out between two Gabions, was unfortunately wounded with a Muſquet-ſhot in his right Thumb, the Cheek and Shoulder, but not dangerouſly: however he preſently cauſed his Thumb to be cut off, becauſe the Bone was broken. About twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or thirty were this day wounded in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burghers</hi> Attack.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1. A Battery was finiſhed upon the Roundel, upon which were planted two pieces of Cannon. In the Morning was ſprung the third Mine, near the ſaid Roundel, but tho' it ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded well, yet there was no other Attempt made, becauſe the Trench was not ſufficiently fill'd; whereupon a Reſolution was taken to fill it up with Faggots, ſacks of Earth, and ſuch like Materials. Our Miners Yeſterday ſmelt ſuch a noyſom Stench in one of their Mines that they were ſcarce able to abide at their Work, till they had remov'd two Bodys that were half dead. About Noon we received intelligence that ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Turks were poſted at <hi>Sexaritwan,</hi> thirteen Leagues from <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> and that the Grand Vizier had begun to paſs the Bridg of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeck</hi> with an Army which he had form'd out of the Gariſons of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and places adjoyning, and other Campanies got toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by force, among which were ſeven thouſand men drawn out of <hi>Boſſina;</hi> and that of eight thouſand Janiſaries which the Grand Vizier had brought from the middle of <hi>Turkie,</hi> three thouſand had deſerted him in his March; that nevertheleſs he hoped to be at the Head of fifty thouſand men, for the Relief of <hi>Buda.</hi> General <hi>Dunewald</hi> return'd this Evening with the Regiments of Horſe, with which he had been ſcouting toward the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain Intelligence of the Enemy. The Generals <hi>Caraffa</hi> and <hi>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> arrived alſo from <hi>Zolnock,</hi> after two days March, with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98375:25"/>five thouſand Horſe, and ſome Hungarian Companies. The next day Count <hi>Budiani</hi> arrived with two thouſand <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngarians;</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent expreſs Orders to General <hi>Scherffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi> to joyn him with his Body of ten thouſand Men. About this time his moſt ſerene Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> had had ſome two or three Fits of an Ague: However he failed not to appear every day in the Trenches, and to give all neceſſary Orders for the carrying on the Siege: To which purpoſe great Preparations were made for a ſecond Onſet upon the ſecond Wall. This Morning the <hi>Bavarians</hi> beat down a great part of the Wall with their Cannon, and by the ſpringing of a Mine; and made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of the ſecond Swinger, where they alſo ſeized upon the Cannons and Mortar Pieces of the Enemy, which they turned upon the City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> 2. They continued filling up the Trench; and every thing was ready for an Aſſault, which was delay'd by reaſon of the continual Rains that fell. Upon repeated Advice of the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Grand Vizier, who, as our Scouts aſſured us, had paſs'd the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> all neceſſary Preparations were made to receive the Enemy, in caſe they attempted to relieve the Town.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> 3. A Deſerter, who affirm'd himſelf to be a Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic Servant to one of the moſt conſiderable Officers in the City, ſurrendered himſelf, and declared that the Beſieged had a Mine ready to ſpring in the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> Attack, and had begun a ſecond: That they impatiently expected Relief: And that of all thoſe whom the Baſſa had ſent abroad, not one was returned into the City, which very much perplexed him; and that the number of ſerviceable Soldiers ſtill exceeded two thouſand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Inhabitants. The Miners could not finiſh the grand Mine, by reaſon of a Rock which they met with. But upon the Breaches certain little Banks were made, to the end the Soldiers might fire with greater Advantage upon the Beſieged during the Aſſault, which was ordered after the following manner. About Noon the Trenches were reliev'd, and they that were relieved were to ſerve as a Reſerve. The firſt Attack was on the right Hand of the Roundel, to which were appointed fifty Granadeers under a Captain, a Lieutenant, and a Serjeant, followed by twenty men that carryed great ſtore of Granado's. They were followed by fifty Fuſeleers, under a Captain, a Lieutenant, and a Serjeant; and after them march'd fifty men with Hatchets. The
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98375:25"/>ſame Order was obſerved by the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> on the left Hand. To the third Attack of the midle Curtain, the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians</hi> were aſſign'd, preceded by thirty <hi>Germans,</hi> and followed by ſixty, with neceſſary Officers. The Onſet began between five and ſix in the Evening, in the Preſence of all the Generals, the grand Maſter of the Teutonic Order commanding the Trench. They forbore to make any falſe Attack, becauſe the Mine had not done that Execution that was expected. But the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> being informed by an Adjutant that the Elector of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia</hi> had abſolutely begun the Aſſault, commanded that the falſe Attack ſhould be chang'd into a formal Onſet. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat laſted two hours, in which three hundred Horſemen that ſerv'd on foot, behav'd themſelves with great valour, as did alſo the <hi>Hungarians.</hi> But the Breach being hard to mount, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged well defended with Paliſadoes, and fighting like men in deſpair, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> would not hazard more men to maintain the inner Breach, where our men had lodged themſelves already, and therefore ſounded a Retreat, contenting himſelf with making a Lodgment on the right hand of the Roundel of the Angle, where forty men entrenched themſelves forthwith. We had few men kill'd by the Enemies firing, but about two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred wounded with Stones and Arrows, which flew like Hail about the Aſſailants Ears. Count <hi>Leopold</hi> of <hi>Herberſtein,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel to <hi>Souches,</hi> was dangerouſly wounded; the Sieur <hi>Biſchop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhauſen,</hi> Serjeant-Major in the Regiments of <hi>Suabia,</hi> carrying his Arm in a Scarf by reaſon of a former wound, was again wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the hand. Nor were the <hi>Bavarians</hi> in their Attack leſs pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd with Stones and Arrows, and the Splinters of Bombs which the Enemy rowl'd down upon the Planks out of the windows of the Caſtle, though to little purpoſe, ſo that the loſs on that ſide was not very conſiderable. The Prince of <hi>Savoy</hi> was wounded in the hand with an Arrow, together with three Captains, ſome inferiour Officers, ſeven or eight Volunteers, and ninety Soldiers killed and wounded. Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Baden</hi> going in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to viſit the Approaches, received a Muſquet-ſhot, which burnt his <hi>Juſtocore,</hi> and very much bruiſed his Breaſt, but the ſtrength of his Armour preſerved him from death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 4th. They fired with a redoubled Force from all three Attacks to enlarge the Breaches and ruin the Enemies De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. The Line of Circumvallation was alſo finiſhed, and ſtrengthned with ſeveral Redoubts and ſmall Forts to flank their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98375:26"/>Works. The <hi>Imperialiſts, Bavarians,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> were alſo ordered to poſſeſs themſelves of all the higher Grounds, where they might entrench to advantage. The <hi>Heydukes</hi> were poſted all along the inner Wall of the low Town, and thus they continued their Attacks with the ſame vigour as before. The <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varians</hi> raiſed a Battery of nine Pieces of four and twenty pound Ball upon the Roundel of the Caſtle, with which they battered the Flanks, and widen'd the Breach; for in regard the Ground is very narrow, the Enemy had the more advantage to diſpute the Entrance of our Men. This day our Scouts brought Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> that the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> had actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſed the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> and that he had twenty thouſand fighting men about his Perſon, which, with the Forces that lay near <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> would make between forty and fifty thouſand men, for the moſt part <hi>Veteranes</hi> drawn out of the Garriſons of Cities and Fortreſſes; in whoſe room he had put his new Levies and forc'd Men. We had alſo Intelligence the ſame day, that the <hi>Baſha</hi> of <hi>Agria,</hi> having drawn together about a thouſand <hi>Turks</hi> out of the Garriſons of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Hungary,</hi> was come to <hi>Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wan,</hi> where he had commanded a great number of Waggons to be laden with Ferry-boats, to be carried to the <hi>Danaw,</hi> by the means of which he deſigned to put in a Reinforcement into <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> at the ſame time that the <hi>Vizier</hi> aſſail'd our Lines on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide. Upon which Intelligence all precautions imaginable were uſed to prevent the Deſigns of the Enemy, and ſecure the River on <hi>Peſt</hi> ſide.</p>
            <p>The 5th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack they carried on their Approaches of the great Roundel toward the ſecond Wall, where they had lodged themſelves after the laſt Aſſault. The Miners were alſo ſet to work under the grand Roundel on the right hand of the Breach, to enable us to attack the Enemy in Flank: and in two other parts on the left hand under the Curtin, to blow up the Entrenchments of the Beſieged behind the Breach. The ſame day they began to build a Gallery, to give a Paſſage to the inner Trench; and the better to ſecure the Attack, Pali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadoes were fixed to the Flanks of our Works. This night the Beſieged did nothing but throw Bombs, Granadoes, and Stones to diſturb our Workmen; but all the hurt they did, was the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of three <hi>Heydukes,</hi> and wounding ſix or ſeven other Soldiers, In the Afternoon one of their Bombs lighted upon a Barrel of Powder, upon one of the Batteries, which kill'd five, and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded three of our Men.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:98375:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſixth of Auguſt.</hi> A new Battery of two Demy Cannons was raiſed in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, behind the great Roundel, by means of which the Defence of the little Roundel was ruined, which had done us great Miſchief. They alſo continued filling up the inner Trench with Bavins, Barrels, Sacks of Earth, and the like. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> and <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> vigurouſly continued their Approaches; but nothing elſe conſiderable paſſed this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aug.</hi> 7. Laſt Night we had ſeveral falſe Alarums, as if the Turks had been at hand to attempt the Relief of the Town; which cauſed us to labor hard in deepning the Trenches round about the Lines, and fortifying the Poſts, to diſcourage the Enemy from any deſign to force our Camp. The Miners alſo were hard at work to get the Mines ready within the next three or four days. The <hi>Heydukes</hi> undertook in twenty four hours time to fill up the Trench of the ſecond Wall, for a Reward of four thouſand Florins, which was promiſed them by the Generals. And now the Breach in the ſecond Wall was very much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, which made the Generals reſolve upon a ſecond Aſſault, ſo ſoon as the Mines ſhould be ready. In the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack they met with great Difficulty to make themſelves Maſters of the Caſtle, by reaſon of the ſeveral Walls and Defences which they had to force, and the obſtinate Oppoſition of the Beſieged, which made the Elector reſolve to redouble his Cannon Batteries. And indeed they did nothing elſe but batter the Caſtle with ſeveral Batterles; which play'd upon the Flanks and Curtins, that it could not be expected they ſhould ſtand long. This day his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoral Highneſs having ſent abroad a Party of thirty <hi>Huſſars,</hi> to gain Intelligence of the Enemy, they met an equal Party of the Turks, whom they purſued for two whole Hours together; but the Enemy was ſo ſwift of Heel, that they could only kill one, and take four Priſoners whom they brought to the Camp. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe Priſoners there was an Aga, that four Years ago had been releas'd out of <hi>Raab</hi> for a Ranſom of eight thouſand Crowns. Theſe Priſoners declared that the Seralquier would be at <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> with twenty ſix thouſand Horſe, and would be followed by the Grand Vizier who was randevouzing his Army near the bridg of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> which would not be inferior to that which we brought laſt year to the Siege of <hi>Gran.</hi> They added likewiſe that the Seraſquier had Orders not to engage in a Battle with the Chriſtians, for fear of loſing the City of <hi>Buda</hi> and the Army both at once; only that he ſhould endeavor to put in a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98375:27"/>Reinforcement of Men into the Town, upon peril of his Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> 8. In the Morning four thouſand Turks and Tartars, Horſe, ſhew'd themſelves upon a high riſing Ground, juſt againſt the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Quarter, and then retreated after ſome ſlight Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes with Count <hi>Budiani's Huſſars,</hi> reinforced with ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Troops and Volunteers. The Priſoners then taken de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> lay encamped under the Cannon of <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> with twenty thouſand fighting Men, where he expected the Grand Vizier with the Body of the Army. But by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of our Spies and Courriers, we were inform'd that the Grand Vizier wavered whether he ſhould paſs any farther with the whole Army, or whether he ſhould ſtay at the Bridge of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeck</hi> with the greateſt part of his Forces, to make head againſt the <hi>Croats,</hi> who might ruin the Bridge if he forſook it, and by that means cut off his Retreat. However it were, to prevent the worſt, we continued fortifying our Camp, and playing with our Cannon and Mortar Pieces againſt the City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>August</hi> 9. Some thouſands of Turks poſted themſelves ſome Leagues from our Camp in a very advantageous place, as if they intended to make ſome Attempt, but we were every way provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for their Coming: Beſides that the Souldiers were very Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, and wiſhed for nothing ſo much as to come to Blows with the Enemy. However becauſe the Enemy gave us ſuch frequent Alarums, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ordered that all the Foot that was not in the Approaches, ſhould be diſpoſed of within the Lines, and particularly in the Spurs of the Fortification. This Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Bomb from the Beſieged unfortunately lighting upon a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of our Granado's, ſet fire to it, and killed three, and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thirteen of our Men. This Evening ſome of the Turks ſhewed themſelves again upon the right Hand, behind the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Camp. Toward which two Squadrons of the Enemy advanced to outbrave our Men; but ſome of our Volunteers ſallying forth with a Reſolution to encounter them, they retreated with the loſs only of one Man ſlain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> 10. They wrought hard to finiſh the third Mine in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, the other two Mines being now ready to play. His Highneſs cauſed the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Infantry to be poſted all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Wall of the low Town; from the water-Roundel to the <hi>German</hi> Quarters, where they ſecured themſelves with a deep Trench and a good Parapet: And becauſe the <hi>Danaw</hi> is very deep thereabout, two Barks filled with Stones were ordered to be
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98375:27"/>ſunk, and ſeveral Paliſado'd Spurs were rais'd all along the bank of the River, to diſcourage the Enemy from deſigning any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief that way. This morning the Enemy gave us another Alarm in the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Quarter: whereupon all our Cavalry were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to horſe; but the Enemy retreated at the ſame time. It ſeems their deſign was to have forced a Paſſage that way; but the <hi>Bavarians</hi> were too well entrenched for them to ſucceed in their Enterprize. The Prince of <hi>Croy</hi> being cured of his wounds, re-entred upon the Duty of his Employment, and appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the Approaches. Four <hi>Huſſars</hi> very well mounted, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing toward ſome <hi>Turks</hi> of the Garriſon, made a ſhew as if they intended to have charg'd 'em, but when they drew near, they talked lovingly together, and ſhook hands: which being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by ſome of the Muſqueteers in the Redoubt adjoyning, they went forth and fired upon the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſars,</hi> who betook themſelves to their heels; but one was wounded and taken Priſoner, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with another of his Companions, the third eſcaped, and the fourth got into the Town. The Priſoners examined, declared that they only expoſtulated with the <hi>Turks</hi> about their holding out; but then they were put off to a more ſtrict Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> 11. Some Troops of the Enemy ſhewed themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hill next to the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Quarters, toward the Road to <hi>Alba Regalis.</hi> As yet we could not learn the exact number of the Enemy, though our Spies aſſured us that they were forty thouſand <hi>Turks,</hi> and twenty thouſand <hi>Tartars.</hi> But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all theſe hot Alarms, being ſo well fitted to receive 'em as we were, all things were at the ſame time preparing for a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Aſſault of the ſecond Wall, if the Mines did that execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as was expected.</p>
            <p>The 12th. In the morning all things being ready for an On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, three Mines were ſprung in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, which did no other Execution, than only overthrew ſome Paliſadoes. For the Miners had not digged deep enough under the Wall of the ſecond Rampart; which made it apparent that they did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their Trade, though the beſt were ſought out and ſent for from ſeveral Parts, the Generals knowing that nothing would contribute more to the Reduction of this Place than well ordered Mines. Thereupon the Aſſault which was determined to have been given, had the Mines ſucceeded, was delay'd, and the Miners were again ſet to work to make new ones. In the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98375:28"/>Skirmiſhes which our Men had this Day with the Enemy, there was a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Officer ſlain, who was no doubt obliged to have got into the Town. For there were Letters found about him, for the Governour of <hi>Buda,</hi> diſcovering the Method which the Enemy intended to obſerve, for the relief of the Town, which was to force one Quarter, and put Relief into the Town, without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding a Battle; and that eight Thouſand <hi>Tartars</hi> were to range the Country, as far as <hi>Gran,</hi> and cut off Proviſion from our Men, and infeſt the Country with continual Inroads Upon which Intelligence, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> called a Council of War. Whereupon it was reſolved to leave a part of the Army to guard the Poſts againſt the City, and to iſſue forth out of the Lines with the reſt of the Imperial, and Auxiliary Forces, and go and meet the Enemy, who, as thoſe Letters ſeemed to intimate, was above ſixty Thouſand Strong. Though the more Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious would not allow 'em to be above forty Thouſand Fighting Men.</p>
            <p>The 13th. All the Army march'd out of the Lines, except twenty thouſand men that were left for the guard of our Works, and to hinder the Enemy from putting a Recruit into the Place. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary-General <hi>Rabata</hi> caus'd a diſtribution of Oats and Hay for the Horſes for three days: And beſides we made a ſhift to form a very noble Body of Volunteers under good Officers. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> poſted himſelf in view of the Enemy, four thouſand <hi>Huſſars</hi> and <hi>Heydukes</hi> keeping the Van-guard. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the Town was no leſs vigorouſly batter'd and aſſail'd than before. This Evening our Spies and ſome Deſerters aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd us that the night following the Enemy would put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Battle-Array, to Attack us the next morning by break of day, which oblig'd the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to diſpoſe all things in readineſs for a Battel.</p>
            <p>The 14th. Before Sun riſe the Enemy had drawn out a Body of eight thouſand Men, part Janiſaries, part Spahi's, of the ſtouteſt and moſt reſolute Soldiers in the Army, which being divided into divers leſſer Bodies, march'd from ſix till eight a Clock in the Morning, turning and winding to and again be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Mountains towards <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> and entred into a Plain, deſigning to approach our Camp under the ſhelter of a great Valley. But the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having obſerv'd this contrivance of the Enemy, and underſtanding their deſign, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Count <hi>Dunewald,</hi> General of the Cavalry, to poſſeſs
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98375:28"/>himſelf of the ground on the left hand, with nine Imperial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments, Cuiraſſiers, Dragoons, and Croats, <hi>viz. Caprara</hi>'s, <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy's, Taff's, Lodron's, Neuburgh's, Furſtenbergh's, Stirum's, Serau's,</hi> and <hi>Schultz's;</hi> to which he added ſome <hi>Huſſars;</hi> and General <hi>Heuſler</hi> had orders to poſt himſelf with his detachment upon a riſing ground on the right hand. The <hi>Huſſars</hi> next to General <hi>Dunewald</hi> were they that received the firſt Charge, and although they fought with all the bravery imaginable, they were never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs forced to give ground; but finding themſelves ſeconded by the <hi>Germans,</hi> they return'd to the Charge. The <hi>Turks</hi> having thus made the <hi>Huſsars</hi> give ground, thought they ſhould have a cheap bargain of the reſt. To which purpoſe they advanced with great fury, and loud outcries, againſt our Men, who recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them without moving a foot: General <hi>Heuſler,</hi> who had the upper ground, charged them vigorouſly; ſo that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat was obſtinate and bloody: for though the Enemies ſaw themſelves attack'd in Flank and Front, they did their utmoſt to cut their way through, till at length they were put into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, ſeparated, and conſtrain'd to fly: The ſlaughter that followed was very great; and it was a very pleaſant ſight to ſee the Janiſaries drop here and there, who being abandon'd by the Spahi's, and environ'd by ours, threw down their Arms and ſhifted every one for themſelves. They were purſu'd into the Plain; nor would it ſerve their Turn, to throw themſelves among the Buſhes to ſhelter themſelves from death; for they were Maſſacred like Wild Beaſts that fall into the Hunters Net. The <hi>Turks</hi> had three Thouſand Men killed upon the Spot, the moſt part <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> and all choice Men, who had undertaken to force a Quarter, and get into the City, or to periſh; and to whom the Grand Vizier had given five Ducats a Head of Twenty, which he promiſed to every one that ſhould enter the City. They car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried almoſt every one of them three Granadoes apiece, a Pickaxe. and a Shovel, to break down our Entrenchments, and fill up the Trenches. The number of the Wounded was very conſiderable; but there were not above five Hundred taken Priſoners. There were taken thirty Colours and Enſigns, and eleven pieces of Cannon, and ten Waggons laden with Ammunition.</p>
            <p>All which coſt us but little Blood; we not having above ſixty Slain; among which were the Count of <hi>Lodron,</hi> General <hi>Lodron</hi>'s Brother, <hi>Caprara's</hi> Serjeant <hi>Major,</hi> and one of <hi>Dunewald</hi>'s Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains: Of the number of the Wounded were two Captains, and thirty three Soldiers.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:98375:29"/>
            <p>This Fight thus over to our Advantage, the Enemy made ſeveral Motions, and ranged themſelves in a Plain that looks to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Quarter, and poſting their Wings-upon the riſing Grounds, made a Shew as if they intended either to come to a Battel, or relieve the Place with all their Forces. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a Council of War, wherein it was reſolved to purſue the Enemy, which was undertaken by the Elector of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> at the Head of his Army: but the ſhortneſs of the time would not permit him to draw up his Men in a formal Array: ſo that the <hi>Turks</hi> doubtful of his deſign, retired. The two Generals, <hi>Dunewald,</hi> and <hi>Heuſler,</hi> purſued the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy beyond the Hills; and the <hi>Huſſars</hi> alſo had a Rencounter with a conſiderable Party of the <hi>Turks</hi> that ſtayed behind to favour the Retreat of the Army. Several Colours and Standards likewiſe were found ſcattered along the Fields, which the Fugitives had thrown away, the better to make their Eſcape. After this Victory, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> commanded ſome Companies to beat the little Woods and Buſhes adjoining, where they found ſeveral <hi>Turks,</hi> who were all put to the Sword. For they had all the Spoil of the Enemy; among whom there was hardly one that had not the five Duckets which the Grand Vizier had given him, beſides his other Mony. The beſieged believing themſelves already reliev'd, fired continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon thoſe that guarded the Approaches, and thought to have ruin'd ſome of our Works; but in vain, for they were ſtill ſo briskly receiv'd, that they had no Maw to hazard skirmiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any more. However they made one furious Sally upon the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack, which prov'd very fatal to 'em, for they were not only repulſed by the Regiments of <hi>Baden,</hi> and <hi>Aſprem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> but their retreat being cut off, there was a great Slaughter made of them. And now the Enemy being retired without daring to come to any deciſion of the diſpute, the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> drew all his Army within the Lines again, and diſpatched away the young Count <hi>Palſi,</hi> Captain in Count <hi>Palſi</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to carry the News to the Emperor, and to lay at his Feet twenty eight Colours and Standards won from the Enemy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the fight. The reſt were ſet up upon the great Roundel, to let the beſieged underſtand the defeat of their Succours, which they expected with ſo much impatience.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:98375:29"/>
            <p>The 15th. The <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Hungariaus</hi> that were upon the Scout, brought ſeveral Priſoners to the Camp which they found in the Woods: they aſſured us, that though the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> had received this Repulſe, he would not fail to make other At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to ſuccour the Town, though he loſt his whole Army by Piecemeals: and in truth, though the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army were a little retreated, yet they fail'd not to Alarm our Camp every night. This afternoon, order was given by the Generals to hang out a Signal, for a Parley by an Interpreter, to let them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> who were Priſoners, the Defeat of their Succours: but whether the Beſieged perceived it, or no; they returned their Anſwer by the Mouths of their great Guns and Muſquets, with which they broke the Staff of a Turkiſh En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign planted upon the great Roundel.</p>
            <p>The 16th. They carried on vigorouſly the Works of the three Attacks, and in the morning ſet fire to the Paliſadoes and the Defences which the Beſieged had made upon the Breaches of the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, notwithſtanding all the diligence of the Enemy to quench it: On the other ſide, while theſe things were a doing, the Enemy threw down a moſt dreadful quantity of Stones, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadoes, Powder-bags, and other artificial Fire-works, upon our men; ſo that four of thoſe that ſet fire to the Paliſadoes were kill'd and burnt. A Recompence of twelve Crowns was given to every Soldier engaged in that Action. But in regard the Onſet could not yet be given, the Enemy had leiſure to fix new Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſadoes, and repair their Defences in the night. On the <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> ſide they inceſſantly battered the Caſtle and the great Tower, which by this time were ready to tumble, through the force of the Battery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>August</hi> 17. All things were ready for an Aſſault betimes in the morning, but the Enemy having repaired their Defences, and put double Paliſadoes behind thoſe that were burnt the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we were conſtrained to deſiſt. The Priſoners which our <hi>Huſſars</hi> brought to the Camp, report that the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> was extreamly enraged againſt the Commander of the <hi>Spahi</hi>'s, for not having done his Duty, in forſaking the <hi>Janiſaries:</hi> to which they added, That of ten thouſand that were employed in the Attempt, very few were return'd to the Camp.</p>
            <p>The 18th. Two great Mines were ſprung in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack; but neither did that Execution which our Miners expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which much retarded the Reduction of the Place. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98375:30"/>the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> finding ſo little progreſs made by the Miners, was reſolved upon the <hi>Sapp;</hi> and to that effect great Preparations were made of Bavins, Sacks of Earth, and the like, to fill up the Trench; and certain Engins were likewiſe contriv'd to approach the Enemy with leſs danger, and to drive them from their Poſts. There was alſo a new Battery raiſed to cut off the Paliſadoes of the Beſieged with chained Bullets. This day a Deſerter came from the Turkiſh Army, who informed us that the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> was encamped at <hi>Ertſchin,</hi> four Leagues from our Camp; but that however he had not given over his deſign of ſuccouring the Beſieged; and that he Retreated only for want of Forrage. This day the <hi>Bavarians</hi> alſo ſeized a Country-man, who had ſwam croſs the <hi>Danaw,</hi> with Letters from the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Buda</hi> for the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> wherein he conjured him by the Law of <hi>Mahomet</hi> to Relieve him; adding, that he would hold out to the laſt Extremity.</p>
            <p>The 19th. The Enemy being thus reſolved to hold out to the laſt gaſp, fired all the day long with their Artillery upon the new Battery raiſed in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack, to beat down the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſadoes fixed upon the Breaches, upon which were planted four Pieces of Canon, and made it unſerviceable; ſo that we were forced to ſtay till night before we could repair it. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachments of the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi>'s Army alarm'd us every night; ſo that for the greater ſecurity of our Camp, we had always ſome Regiments upon the Guard, to prevent the Deſings of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and to be ready upon all Occaſions. Moreover, it was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily thought that ſo ſoon as General <hi>Scherffenbergh</hi> ſhould arrive in the Camp with his Body of men out of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> where he had garriſon'd ſome Caſtles, that the Duke would attack the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> in his Camp, who, by the Report of all the Priſoners and Deſerters, was not above ſix and forty thouſand men, of which the one half were forc'd and undiſciplin'd Men. In the mean time he was very vigilant to ſend out conſiderable Parties to obſerve the Motion of the Enemy, who every foot meeting with the Turks, gain'd every day ſome remarkable Advantage over 'em.</p>
            <p>The 20th. The Grand Vizier deſirous once more to try to put Relief into <hi>Buda,</hi> reſolved to attempt with a leſſer Body than before, that he might not be ſo eaſily diſcovered, and might approach our Camp before we had notice of it. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he made choice of the ſtouteſt Officers of his Army, who
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98375:30"/>promiſed to obey his Commands, or periſh in the Attempt. Theſe Men ſet forward in the Night time with two thouſand <hi>Spahi's,</hi> and an equal number of <hi>Janiſeries</hi> for the more ſpeed. And this morning by break of day they appeared in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Valley. Where having put themſelves in order without being perceived, they came thundring upon our Out-Guards with loud Cries and terrible Yelling, and having eaſily forc'd them, fell upon two Squadrons of <hi>Caprara</hi>'s and <hi>Heuſler</hi>'s Cavalrie, who received 'em briskly, and gave opportunity to others to come to their Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and repel the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> who fled as faſt as their Horſes Heels could carry them. The <hi>Janiſaries</hi> alſo, ſome of whom were already alighted, with an Intention to break through our Lines and get into the City, were very courſely entertain'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purſu'd by General <hi>Heuſler</hi> to the very Gate, and met by the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Horſe-Guard, who came running in upon the Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum; ſo that the Slaughter of the Enemy was very great, and very few had the good Luck to enter the City. For tho' ſome will have them to be a hundred and fifty, hardly a hundred had that good Fortune, which it was eaſy to judg by the Horſes that were quitted, which exceeded not the ſame number, and beſides a good part of them were wounded too by the Musket ſhot of our Souldiers in the Approaches, by which there was a neceſſity for 'em to paſs. And indeed had the Out-Guards done their Duty, not a <hi>Turk</hi> had paſſed our Lines. The Enemy had above four hundred ſlain; and of our Men there were about fifteen ſlain, and twenty ſeven wounded. General <hi>Heuſler,</hi> who behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with an extraordinary Gallantry, received a Wound in the Foot, but not dangerous; but General <hi>Maigret</hi> was very much cut and mangled with a Scirnitar. The Marqueſs <hi>Santini,</hi> Knight of <hi>Malta,</hi> and Captain in <hi>Salleburgh</hi>'s Regiment, was taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in the firſt Onſet. And now the Beſieged to teſtify their Joy for the Relief they had received, hung out three red Colours in ſign of Victory, and fir'd three Rounds of all their great and ſmall Shot. During the Combat ſome Squadrons of Horſe of the Grand Vizier's Army, who had followed the reſt, to ſecond them if Occaſion were, ſhew'd themſelves in Battel Array to the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack, making a ſhew as if they intended to try their Fortune on that ſide, but they retired without enterprizing any thing. But at ten a Clock at Night they returned again to the ſame place where they had attempted to break through in the Morning; but were repulſed by our Men, and retired in Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98375:31"/>Within the Lines, the <hi>Bavarians</hi> raiſed a new Battery of four pieces of Cannon in their Attack, and the Beſieged planted a whole Cannon upon the high Wall of the Caſtle, with which they battered all the Covert way, as alſo the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Battery upon the great Roundel.</p>
            <p>The 21ſt. This Morning a Redoubt was raiſed in that part which the <hi>Turks</hi> forced the day before, planted with two pieces of Cannon, and ſtrengthened with a ſufficient Force to defend the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. Another Redoubt was alſo raiſed upon the Hill upon the left hand, where <hi>Lodron</hi>'s Regiment encamped. This day the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged fired ſome Rounds of great Guns in token of Joy, tho' we could not gueſs the reaſon, unleſs it were for the Celebration of ſome Feſtival. This day alſo the Sieur <hi>Rummel,</hi> General of the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varian</hi> Forces, being in the Approaches, was killed with a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Shot. He was very much lamented, as being an Officer who all along had given moſt ſignal Proofs of his martial Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and fought diſtinguiſhed upon all Occaſions, where he might win Honour.</p>
            <p>The 22d. This Morning the Elector cauſed an Aſſault to be given to the great Tower, which is in the middle of the Caſtle, and which our Artillery had for the moſt part ruin'd; and made himſelf Maſter of it after an hours Diſpute, which coſt us the loſs of ſeventy three men, and as many wounded, among whom was Duke <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Saxon-Mersbergh.</hi> During this Aſſault there was a falſe Alarum given in the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack to divert the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy; and the great Guns fired with great Fury upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences which the Enemy had raiſed upon the Breaches of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Wall. This Evening about ten a Clock a <hi>Turk</hi> was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, who having got out of the Town by ſwimming the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, travelled all along the Banks of the <hi>Danaw;</hi> and was got as far as St. <hi>Margetts</hi> Iſland, where being perceived, he threw his Letters into the River, but nevertheleſs confeſſed that he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched by the Governor to inform the Grand Vizier of the Condition of the Place, and to preſs Relief: Adding withal that there was another got out upon the ſame Errand.</p>
            <p>The 23d. The Beſieged made an Attempt to recover the great Tower of the Caſtle, which the <hi>Elector</hi>'s Forces had won the day before; but they were repulſed, and purſued to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments. In the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack four pieces of Cannon were planted upon the old great Battery, with which they began to batter the new Paliſadoes upon the Breach of the inner Wall.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98375:31"/>Laſt night the Beſieged made a Salley upon the <hi>Saxons</hi> Quarter but were ſo ſmartly received and repulſed by Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Pletze,</hi> who was upon the Guard with a hundred Horſe, that they had much ado to regain their ſecond Wall, where this Officer was ſlain with two Muſquet-ſhots, the one in his ſide, and the other in his head.</p>
            <p>The 24th. This morning the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhewed themſelves in two diſtinct Bodies, one upon the <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and the other next the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Quarters, but without making any attempt they Retreated about Noon to their Camp, which they had removed about a League nearer to ours than it was before. This day a Deſerter aſſured us, that the Beſieged began to talk with a great deal of liberty againſt the Governour, who nevertheleſs endeavoured all he could to retain them in their Duty; aſſuring them that the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> daily expected in his Camp one of the chief Miniſters at the <hi>Port,</hi> called <hi>Michtakis,</hi> with full power from the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> to treat and conclude a Peace with the Generals of the Chriſtian Army: and that upon his arrival there would be a ſuſpenſion of Arms; exhorting 'em not to degenerate at laſt from the Gallantry and Vertue of true <hi>Muſſel-men,</hi> whoſe Honour they had hitherto ſo generouſly maintained, and to tarry a few days longer, before they talk'd of a Surrender.</p>
            <p>The 25. The D. of <hi>Lorrain</hi> being inform'd the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> might find a Paſſage on the ſide of the <hi>Danaw,</hi> behind the hot Bathes, to put a Re-inforcement into the City, ordered that there ſhould be every night ſome Squadrons of Horſe ready to ſecond the Guards, which ſhould be likewiſe doubled; and to render the Paſſage more difficult for the <hi>Turks</hi> to force, he cauſed Paliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does to be fixed in the weaker and moſt defenceleſs places, and cauſed certain <hi>German</hi> and <hi>Hungarian</hi> Squadrons and Battalions to be there poſted, in ſuch a manner, that if the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhould make any attempt elſewhere, they might ſtill be ready with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief whereever the Alarm called. There was alſo ſome alteration made in two Batteries, the better to endamage the Beſieged, and overturn their Parapets, Paliſadoes, and other Defences, which they had raiſed upon the Breach of the inner Wall. The <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varians</hi> were forced to win their ground inch by inch, nor could they as yet make themſelves Maſters of the whole Caſtle; ſuch was the Oppoſition of a ſtout and daring Enemy, who did not loſe a foot of Ground, but what he ſought to regain by ſeveral Efforts, making uſe to that purpoſe of Bombs, Granadoes, Stones, Powder-bags, and all thoſe other means that Courage
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98375:32"/>or Deſpair were capable to invent to the Deſtruction of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailants. Inſomuch that it coſt no ſmall labour, as faſt as we gained Ground, to fill up the Holes and Caverns which the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had hollow'd in the Earth for our ruin; which had it not been done, we had never kept our Stations.</p>
            <p>The 26th. The Priſoners which our Parties brought to the Camp, as well as ſome Deſerters gave us Information, that one of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers which the Governour had ſent to the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> was ſafely arriv'd at the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi>'s Camp, and had deliver'd him the Governor's Letters, wherein he gave him an account of the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the place, that he could not hold out much longer; that the Chriſtians were Maſters of the Caſtle, and that the next Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault would ſurely carry the Place; that at the laſt Aſſault of the Caſtle he had loſt above an hundred of his beſt Soldiers; that the laſt Re-inforcement was very inconſiderable, as not amounting to two hundred men, of which the one half were wounded and unfit for Service; that for his part he had done his duty, in let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Chriſtians know by a Defence ſo obſtinate, during ſo long a Siege, carried on with ſo much fury and bravery on both ſides, that the <hi>Muſſel-men</hi> knew how to defend their <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of which he claimed to have merited the Honour: Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at length that it lay at the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi>'s door to give an account for the ill Succeſs of the Siege, and that he was only to be reſponſable for the loſs ſo conſiderable, which could not be avoided, if the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> attempted one more Aſſault; as alſo for the Blood of his valiant Soldiers, and his own, if he any longer delayed Relief. In the ſame Letter the Governour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> the Place moſt proper for him to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, which was ſo little dreamt of, that if he ordered his Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs as he ought to do, he could not fail in his Enterprize. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Intelligence the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> viſited himſelf the Place mark'd out by the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> to make the Attempt, and put all things in order to prevent the Enemies Deſign. The Spies which were ſent to the Enemies Camp, reported, That the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> had promiſed forty Crowns apiece to thoſe that would undertake to put themſelves into the Town, promiſing moreover, that during their Lives, they ſhould be exempt from going to the Wars, and yet ſhould enjoy their uſual Pay conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without doing any duty. About Noon we had Intelligence that the Enemy advanced with twelve Pieces of Canon, and preſently after they appeared within view of our Camp, drawn up in Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel Array: However no ſooner had the Duke Marſhal'd our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98375:32"/>in a Condition ready to oppoſe 'em, but they retreated again.</p>
            <p>The 27th. In the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack was finiſhed a certain piece of Workmanſhip like a Bridge, which was to be run along up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Wheels to the Enemies Paliſado's in the time of the Onſet: It was covered with Earth to prevent firing, as the day before they had fired ſome Wooden-works of the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> which conſtrain'd 'em to recoil; but this Morning they recovered their former Poſts, and to guard themſelves from the Fire, made uſe of Planks covered with Tin: But when they thought themſelves ſafe from that devouting Element, the Enemy no leſs induſtrious to deſtroy than they to preſerve, flung down in the Evening ſuch an infinite Quantity of Pitch, Tar, Sulphur, and other combuſtible Materials, with that Succeſs, that the Fire got to the Planks, and reduc'd 'em to Aſhes. At the ſame time they alſo caſt down ſuch an infinite Quantity of Granado's, Stones, and Arrows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> that they were conſtrain'd a ſecond time to quit their Poſts with the loſs of twenty Soldiers.</p>
            <p>The 28th. In the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attack they did nothing but bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Flanks of the great Breach, as did alſo the <hi>Brandenburgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> to overturn the Defences of the Enemy. So that at length the <hi>Bavarians</hi> recovered their Poſt, and ſecured it ſo well that it was not in the power of the Enemy to diſlodge 'em any more. Serjeant Major <hi>Stuben,</hi> of the Regiment of <hi>Sebolſtorff,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Aſſailants, was ſlain, with ſome common Soldiers; tho' both ſlain and wounded, did not exceed the number of twenty. Upon the Report of ſome Deſerters, that the grand Vizier was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd this night to attack us with all his Forces, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> prepared all things in a Readineſs to receive him, and all the Army ſtood to their Armes in Battalia; but to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for no Enemy appeared.</p>
            <p>The 29th. Being the Day of St. <hi>John</hi>'s beheading, which the <hi>Turks,</hi> out of a fooliſh piece of Superſtition, have always look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a day auſpicious to their Empire, a thouſand <hi>Spahi</hi>'s, and two thouſand <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> under the command of two <hi>Baſha</hi>'s, and ſeconded by fifteen hundred <hi>Tartars,</hi> came to try their Fortune on that ſide next the Water, but finding thoſe Poſts too well provided, and having been ſaluted with a volley of ſmall Shot, they retired in great haſt, and thought it more proper to try to break through in that part where the laſt Reinforcement had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced their way. In ſhort an hour after they appeared in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Valley, and with terrible Outcries and Yells came thundring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Horſe Regiments of <hi>Mercy, Heuſler,</hi> and <hi>Neuburgh,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98375:33"/>'em with that Gallantry, that they ſlew a great number of thoſe <hi>Barbarians,</hi> of whom ſome were ſo fool-hardy as to throw themſelves into our Lines, where they were all cut to pieces, except 4. who were ſo fortunate as to get into the Town. We reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 600. <hi>Turks</hi> that were ſlain in this Action, beſides the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, which are not very many. There were alſo taken 25. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of Horſe and Foot, all Red, to ſignifie that they would either enter the Town or dye. On our ſide there were not above 30. ſlain and wounded, among which latter was General <hi>Mercy,</hi> having receiv'd two Cuts with a Scimitar, one in the Head, and the other in the Shoulder, tho' nothing dangerous; but his Adjutant-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral was ſlain. During the heat of this Action, the Beſieged made a Sally upon the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack; but the <hi>Heydukes</hi> aſſailing 'em in Flanck, they had much ado to retire with the loſs of 17. killed upon the Place. All this day the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> ſhewed himſelf on the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Quarters, ready to try the Fortune of a Battle, but perceiving the Arrival of General <hi>Picolomini</hi> in our Camp, with three Regiments of Cuiraſſiers, and two of Dragoons, being the Vanguard of General <hi>Scherffenbergh</hi>'s Body, he retreated in great haſt to his Camp.</p>
            <p>The 30th. General <hi>Picolomini</hi> arriving yeſterday with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of <hi>Saxon Lawenburgh, Picolomini,</hi> St. <hi>Croix, Tettwin,</hi> and <hi>Magni,</hi> making in all 25. Squadrons, was this day followed by Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant-General <hi>Scherffenbergh</hi> with the reſt of his Body, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Foot Regiments of <hi>Veterani, Getz, Sereni, Spinola,</hi> and <hi>Scherffenberg,</hi> all luſty proper Men, and well diſciplin'd. The Deſerters alſo aſſur'd us that there was a great Scarcity in the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi>'s Army, and that the Souldiers half ſtarved, had pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laged certain Barks that brought Proviſions for <hi>Buda,</hi> their Officers not being able to prevent it. The 31th. In the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Attacque a new Poſt was taken in the Trench before the Breach of the Inner Wall, which is not above three Fadom diſtance from the Paliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do's of the Beſieged; and in regard the place was very deep, the <hi>Turks</hi> could not annoy us; ſo that we had not above two men wounded. This Morning the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> accompany'd with all the reſt of the Generals, went over to the Elector's Quarters, where he held a Council of War, and after Dinner the Duke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to his own Quarters, where he order'd the Works to be enlarg'd and deepn'd, that they might with leſs difficulty go on to the General Affault, which was then intended within a day or two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sept.</hi> 1. The <hi>Turks</hi> ſhewed themſelves before day by the light of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98375:33"/>the Moon near the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Attack, to the number of 3000 Horſe and Foot; but perceiving our men to be in good order, and ready to receive 'em, they retired without making any attempt. Ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday the Grand Chancellor, the Count <hi>de Straatman,</hi> being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the Camp, with a private Commiſſion from the Emperor, he cauſed a Council of War to be call'd, where were preſent the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and all the Generals, both Imperialiſts and Auxiliaries. The Chancellor then produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his Commiſſion, to this effect; That his Imperial Majeſty earneſtly deſiring an end of that bloody Siege, they were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the moſt proper and expedient means to do it. Thereupon two Points were propoſed; Whether to fight the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> with the greateſt part of the Army, leaving a ſufficient Force to guard the Lines; or, whether to give a general Aſſault to the Place with a greater Force than had yet been made uſe of to that purpoſe. Which latter Propoſal was concluded upon by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the Generals, and ſo a general Aſſault being concluded upon the next day, all things were prepared in a readineſs, that the Blow might not fail; and to keep the Enemy in ignorance, a Rumor was ſpread abroad in the Camp, That the next day the General intended to give the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> Battel, which cauſed great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing among the Officers and Soldiers, who deſired nothing more than to ſignalize their Valour. Nevertheleſs they forbore not to play all the day long from all the Batteries to widen the Breaches, and beat down the Enemies Defences.</p>
            <p>The 2d. All the Generals got on Horſeback, and the Army was drawn up ready to quit the Lines, and march to the grand Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, from thence to march toward the <hi>Grand Vizier.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and the Elector viſited every Quarter, encouraging the Officers and Soldiers valiantly to maintain the Cauſe of God and the Emperor's Honour. In the mean time the Infantry rang'd themſelves in their ſeveral Battalions, the great Guns were fired with re-doubled Fury from all the three Attacks, and an infinite number of Bombs and chain'd Shot were thundred againſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of the Beſieged. But when the Army was juſt ready to march toward the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> of a ſuddain the whole order of the March was chang'd, and about three a Clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon the Rean-Guard was commanded to mount the Breaches, all things being ſo provided before hand, that without diſturbing the Order of the Battalions, they might fall on. Which they did in three ſeveral Places; <hi>viz.</hi> In the <hi>Lorrain, Bavarian,</hi> and <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburghers</hi> Attacks: beſides other falſe Attacks premeditated to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98375:34"/>divert the Enemy: But notwithſtanding all theſe Precautions to render the Aſſault more eaſie, ſuch was the obſtinate Reſiſtance, that they had much ado to prevail. They defended themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three quarters of an hour with their Halbards, Half-pikes, and Partiſans, and ſlung ſuch an infinite quantity of Stones, Arrows and Granadoes, that they repulſed us vigorouſly more than once: but at length our men, encouraged by the Preſence of their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, returned to the Aſſault with greater Fury, and made themſelves Maſters of the Breaches in all the three Attacks. The <hi>Turks</hi> defended themſelves, retreating from Entrenchment to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment, ſo that the ſlaughter was very bloody: for our Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers having driven the <hi>Turks</hi> from their Defences, entred the City by main force, over-run the Streets, put all to the Sword that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred their Fury, ſparing neither Sex nor Age, ſo that there was nothing elſe to be ſeen but the dead Bodies of the ſlain. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> alſo purſued their Advantage, and fell upon a thouſand <hi>Turks</hi> who were retired to a little Fort at the Foot of the Caſtle, where they defended themſelves to the utmoſt, till at length deſpairing of their Safety, they hung out a white Flag, and begg'd for Quarter. Which, conſidering their obſtinacy, and the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had made of our men, the Duke and the Elector were at firſt unwilling to grant; but recollecting afterwards that their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was great, that they might do us more miſchief, that Night drew on; that the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> was at hand with a Formidable Army, that the Soldiers were tired and wanted repoſe, and that the City was on Fire in ſeveral places, they reſolv'd to give them their Lives; of which when theſe miſerable Creatures were aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they flung down their Arms and yielded at diſcretion. There were about a thouſand <hi>Turks</hi> more, who being retired into Caves and Caverns, obtained the ſame favour. The number of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians that were ſlain, amounted to above 3000. beſides the wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which were not many: ſo that it appears the Garriſon was much ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nger than the Deſerters reported. The Governour <hi>Baſha</hi> dy'd bravely upon the the Breach, where he defended himſelf va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly with his Scimiter in his hand, ſcorning to Retreat or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Quarter, that he might not degenerate from the Honour and Heroic Vertue of the ancient <hi>Muſſel men,</hi> nor falſifie the Oath which he had made the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> either to preſerve the Town, or gloriouſly to end his days. The <hi>Vice Baſha,</hi> being an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of high Reputation, defended the Caſtle, but perceiving all was loſt, retir'd fighting into the fore-mentioned Fort at the foot of the Caſtle, which he thought to make good, and give the <hi>Grand Viſier</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:98375:34"/>leiſure to relieve him; but ſeeing the deſperate condition of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, he rather choſe to implore the clemency of the Victors, than to occaſion the Maſſacre of thoſe that were about him, and ſo was taken Priſoner with the reſt by the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> and preſented to his Electoral Highneſs. The <hi>Aga</hi> of the Janiſaries taken by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts, was delivered up to the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Turkiſh Officers of note. So that the number of the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers did not much exceed 2000. Men, of 13000. at the beginning of the Siege, all ſtout and experienc'd Soldiers, and the very ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news of the Militia of all the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire. The loſs on our ſide was very ſmall, compar'd with that of the Enemies. For we cannot reckon above 400. kill'd, and about 200. wounded, among whom were ſeveral Volunteers, but very few Officers, Colonel <hi>Spinola,</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Arquato,</hi> an Officer of great merit, receiv'd his death's wound at the head of the Aſſailants; &amp; the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Aſti,</hi> who had been twice wounded before, during the Siege, receiv'd a third wound more dangerous than any of the former, to the great hazard of his life. The booty which the Soldiers got was extraordinary, there being a vaſt deal of Wealth in the City, which the Inhabitants of other Cities and Places under the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Turk</hi> had brought thither for Security, as being a place which they thought impregnable. There was found in the Town, Ammunition and Proviſion ſufficient for a Siege of two Months longer; a Magazine furniſh'd with all ſorts of Arms Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive and Defenſive for above 30000. Men, Harneſs for Horſes, Saddles, Boots, and other Equipage for the Cavalry; and beſides all this near 400. Pieces of Cannon, and Mortar Pieces, of which 170. were never the worſe, fixed upon their Carriages. It is impoſſible to give you an Inventory of every thing; 'twill be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſay, that never any City could be better provided to ſuſtain a vigorous Siege, than this was; or ever was defended by a ſtouter Garriſon. But if the reſiſtance met with, were ſo ſurprizing, much more muſt be the Glory of ſo many brave Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, Volunteers, and Soldiers, that ſignalized their valour, and eternized, not only their own Memories, but the Honour of the Emperor, in gaining ſuch a ſtrong hold, and recovering it into the Poſſeſſion of him, to whom it belongs by right of Nature and Succeſſion; and which had endured ſo many Sieges, before it could be reduced under the Subjection of its Lawful Sovereign.</p>
            <q>
               <p>BVDA SEXTO INEXPVGNABILIS, SEPTIMO FIT CESARIS</p>
               <p>Buda <hi>ſix times Inexpugnable, the ſeventh becomes</hi> Caeſar's.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:98375:35"/>
            <p>The D. of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> after he had prevented any farther ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and given all neceſſary orders to reduce the Soldiers under their Colours, commanded the People to quench the fire that continu'd burning in ſeveral parts, gave the Government of the place to General <hi>Beek,</hi> with a Garriſon of 5000. Foot, and 1000. Horſe, till his Imperial Majeſty ſhould otherwiſe diſpoſe of the abſolute Government of this Imperial City; and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between 8 and 10000 Cuiraſſiers and Dragoons, with the <hi>Huſſars</hi> under Count <hi>Budiani</hi> to purſue the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> who having look'd on, and ſeen the taking of <hi>Buda,</hi> decamp'd with his whole Army to ſecure the reſt of the Turkiſh Fortreſſes, to reinforce the Garriſons, and gain the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> where our General is reſolv'd to attack him, if he can overtake him in his march. To which purpoſe the Infantry was embark'd upon the <hi>Danaw,</hi> to make the more haſt, while the Cavalry march'd by Land.</p>
            <p>Thus was this great and ſtrong City, the Capital City of all <hi>Hungary,</hi> the ſeat of the Ancient Kings, reduced under the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of our moſt Illuſtrious and Invincible Emperour <hi>Leopold</hi> the firſt, after it had groaned under the Tyrannous Yoke of the <hi>Ottomans</hi> a hundred forty five years, who made uſe of it as a place of Rendezvous for their Armies, and a Magazine to furniſh all the other Cities in thoſe parts under their ſubjection, with Men and Ammunition, to which purpoſe they always furniſhed it with a numerous Garriſon, never conſiſting of leſs than between 8 and 10000 Janiſaries and Spain's, whether in Peace or War. And though Sultan <hi>Solyman</hi> won this important place from King <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand,</hi> Brother to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, in the year 1529. through the treachery of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Garriſon; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he put it into the hand of <hi>John Zapolilia,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania,</hi> who had call'd him to his Aſſiſtance to preſerve him in the Throne, to which he had been advanc'd by Sedition, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Form, by a part of the Nobility, after the death of King <hi>Lewis</hi> ſlain at the Battle of <hi>Mohaes,</hi> contrary to the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the real King <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> duly elected by the four Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the States of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>This Uſurper being thus confirm'd in the enjoyment of one part of the Kingdom, and of the Capital City under the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Turks,</hi> King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> ſent his General Count <hi>Rog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendorff,</hi> who had ſo valiantly defended <hi>Vienna,</hi> under the Command of the Elector Palatine, againſt the efforts of <hi>Solyman,</hi> to lay Siege to <hi>Buda;</hi> but he was conſtrain'd to raiſe his Siege,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98375:35"/>after he had loſt a great part of his Army. General <hi>Felſius</hi> was ſent thither 10. years after. But that Enterpriſe ſucceeded no better tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the former; notwithſtanding the Death of the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Zapolia,</hi> and the Minority of his Son <hi>John Sigiſmund,</hi> who was under the Tutelage of the Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> his Mother, and <hi>George Martinuſius,</hi> chief Miniſter of State to his deceaſed Father. However King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> was no way diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by theſe two unſucceſsful Attempts, but conſidering the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of the Place for the Support of his Crown, reſolv'd upon a third Attempt. To which purpoſe he raiſed a more numerous Army than before, and gave the Command of it to <hi>Roggendorff,</hi> who the next Year laid a third Siege to <hi>Buda,</hi> and had made himſelf Maſter of it, if <hi>Solyman,</hi> at the Sollicitation of the Princeſs <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> had not haſtned to his Relief; which conſtrained the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to raiſe his Siege, not being able to make head againſt ſuch a numerous Army of the Infidels. Thereupon the Sultan politick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeized upon the City of <hi>Buda,</hi> ſent the young Prince <hi>John Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmund,</hi> with the Princeſs his Mother, into <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> and kept the Town in his own Hands, with a Reſolution never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it, notwithſtanding his public Declaration to keep it only during the Minority of the Prince. And to that intent he filled it with a ſtrong Garriſon of his own Men, the choiceſt in his Army, under the Command of a <hi>Beglerbeg,</hi> or <hi>Vice Roy,</hi> whoſe Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty extends over all the <hi>Baſha</hi>'s of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it was that this Royal City has been ever ſince in ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the <hi>Ottoman Empire.</hi> The Marqueſs of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd a deſign upon <hi>Buda</hi> in the Year 1542. but having in vain aſſaulted the City of <hi>Peſt,</hi> which is ſeparated from it only by the <hi>Danaw,</hi> he retreated without making the leaſt Attempt upon the Capital City: So that this Expedition is not to be lookt upon as a Siege, as ſome would erroneouſly have it to be. Count <hi>Smarzen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> beſieg'd it in the Year 1598. but was conſtrain'd to raiſe his Siege after he had lain thirty days before it, by reaſon of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Rains when the Year was too far ſpent. In the Year 1602. General <hi>Roſwourm</hi> lay before it with the Imperial Army, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacqu'd it in vain. Nor was the fatal day for this Place languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingunder the Tyranny of the <hi>Turks,</hi> yet come in the Year 1684. when the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> firſt attacked it. For God had ordain'd the 2d. of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1686. (the day when it was taken by <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>) to be the day of his Triumph, when it was again wreſted from the Hands of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> after this ſame 7th. Siege had been carried on with that Heat, Conſtancy, Prudence, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98375:36"/>of the Couragious D. of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> aſſiſted by the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> no leſs eminent for all the forementioned Vertues, and ſeveral other Generals of the Emperor, and his Auxiliaries, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly conſpiring the Regaining of this Place, that we have reaſon to hope for Conqueſts far more Glorious, and more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable for the Advancement of the Cauſe of God, Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Austrian</hi> Family, and conſolation of ſo great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſtian Souls as groan'd under the Tyrannous Yoak of Infidels, and the Recovery of an infinite number of <hi>Barbarians</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Boſom of the true Church of God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> have heretofore experienced the Valour of <hi>Huniades</hi> and <hi>Scanderbergh,</hi> who were the Scourges of thoſe barbarous Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: They have trembled at the Courage and Conduct of the D. of <hi>Merceur,</hi> to that degree, that the Grand Signior threaten'd a Rupture with <hi>France,</hi> if the King would not recall him out of the Emperor's Service. They have been apprehenſive of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Valiant Count <hi>Serini,</hi> and ſeveral other famous Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, every where attended by their good Fortune. But much more Reaſon have they to be aſtoniſhed at the Heroic Virtues of our undaunted and martial D. of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who ſeems to have been born for the Subverſion of the Mahometan Law, and with whom no Perſon living can diſpute the Honour of being the greateſt Captain of his Age, and the Terror of the <hi>Muſſelmen;</hi> who knows not what it is to loſe a Battel, and who may ſay with the Invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> V. when he ſwam croſs the <hi>Elb,</hi> vanquiſh'd and took Priſoner <hi>Frederic</hi> D. of <hi>Saxony,</hi> crying out, <hi>Veni, vidi, Deus vicit.</hi> For in all Encounters whereever he engaged, during this Holy War, he has miraculouſly triumphed o're his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and born away the Victory. He it was, who during the Seige of <hi>Vienna,</hi> ſurpriz'd and overcame near <hi>Presburgh</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Army of Perfidious <hi>Teckley,</hi> Reinforced with a Body of <hi>Turks</hi> under the Command of <hi>Huſſein-Baſha.</hi> He it was that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated the <hi>Turks</hi> near <hi>Calenburgh,</hi> and conſtrain'd the Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier diſhonourably to raiſe his Siege from before <hi>Vienna.</hi> He it was that vanquiſhed the Enemy near <hi>Barkan,</hi> and reſcu'd the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Prince his Son, when they were both in iminent Danger, and the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Army in Confuſion. He it was that during the Siege of <hi>Buda</hi> three times defeated the Seraſquier's Army: Who during the Siege of <hi>Newhauſel</hi> relieved the City of <hi>Gran,</hi> and routed the Army of <hi>Zeitan Ibraim Baſſa.</hi> And laſtly, he it was who won this glorious Conqueſt, while the Grand Vizi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Solyman</hi> looked on with a potent Army of <hi>Barbarians,</hi> twice
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98375:36"/>or thrice beat his Succors, and tho' at length he came up with all his Forces againſt our Lines, gave a general Aſſault, and by main Force carried this Important Place, guarded ſtill by above 5000. fighting Men; So that it is deſervedly ſaid of him,</p>
            <q>
               <p>EXPVLIT EX BVDA TVRCAM.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He drave the Turk out of</hi> Buda.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Conqueſts made in <hi>Turkie</hi> are the price of ſo many Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and will doubtleſs be attended with many more by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the God of Battels, who has hitherto favour'd and bleſs'd the victorious Arms of our thrice Illuſtrious Monarch, under the Conduct of ſo great a Captain, defcended from the Noble Stock of ſo many Illuſtrious Hero's, and particularly from the warlike Conqueror of the Holy Land, <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bulloign,</hi> whoſe ſteps he treads ſo gloriouſly, that if the Chriſtian Princes would but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him with their Forces, and act unanimouſly with him, he might with eaſe regain the Kingdom of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> his ancient Patrimony, which the Infidels wreſted from his Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>Would it might pleaſe Divine Providence that now the time were come to humble the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, which according to the Prognoſtications of the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves, has not long to ſubſiſt, it being a Prediction currant among 'em, <hi>That the City of</hi> Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople <hi>having been taken by one</hi> Mahomet, <hi>will be re-taken by the Chriſtians under the Raign of another</hi> Mahomet. God grant that this may happen under Him at preſent, who by the loſs of <hi>Buda</hi> has loſt the Key of all his Empire. Nor will it be amiſs to add in this place the following Epigram, made by an ingenious Perſon upon this Subject.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Integra de Victis foret ut Victoria Turcis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Littera Chriſticolis,</hi> B, <hi>capienda ter eſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Buda <hi>prius, poſthanc</hi> Belgradum, <hi>Regia demum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maenia</hi> Byſanti, <hi>caetera luſus erunt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O're conquer'd Turks the Victory to compleat,</l>
               <l>The Chriſtians thrice muſt Letter <hi>B</hi> repeat.</l>
               <l>Firſt <hi>Buda, Belgrade</hi> next, the third Effort</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Byſantium</hi>'s Walls, the reſt will be but Sport.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>That is to ſay, that before we can gain an abſolute Triumph over
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98375:37"/>the <hi>Turks,</hi> and ruin their Empire, the Chriſtians muſt win the three Principal Cities of their Empire that begin with the Letter <hi>B, Buda, Belgrade,</hi> and <hi>Byſantium;</hi> the reſt will come eaſily. <hi>Buda,</hi> which is the ſtrongeſt of all theſe three places, is already taken, as you have heard, and by the Recovery of this Important Place, the Gate is open to <hi>Belgrade,</hi> there being no Fortreſs upon the <hi>Danaw</hi> able to diſpute our Approach; and the advantage of that River will not a little contribute to facilitate an Enterprize of ſo great Importance to all Chriſtendom. <hi>Byſantium</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> alſo might be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily attacked, both by Sea and Land; while the Naval Power of the moſt Serene Republick of <hi>Venice,</hi> re-inforced with the Galleys of the Pope, <hi>Malta, Tuſcany,</hi> and others, force the <hi>Dardanels,</hi> and block it up by Sea. The <hi>Polonian</hi> Army alſo croſſing <hi>Beſſarabia,</hi> might march as far as the <hi>Pontus Euxinus,</hi> and awe thoſe Countries which for many Ages have not known what War is, nor ſeen an Enemy. For if a handful of <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> that inhabit the Rocks of <hi>Borysthenes,</hi> during the late Wars of <hi>Poland,</hi> have been ſo coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious as to affront with their ſmall Barks the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> in his <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and alarm <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> it ſelf, the Capital City of the Empire, and to fire the very Suburbs: what might not ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Armies of ſo many Chriſtian Princes be able to do, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by ſo many remarkable Victories which they have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained over their Enemies, and the famous Conqueſts they have won under the Conduct of ſuch Renowned Captains, who know nothing elſe but how to Conquer; eſpecially at a time when the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and the Grand Duke of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> are preparing to make moſt powerful Diverſions in favour of the Chriſtians?</p>
            <closer>TIBI DEVS EXERCITVVM GLORIA SIR AEVITERNA. <hi>To thee, O God of Battel, be Eternal Glory.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98375:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
